<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prince of Conde made English.</title>
            <title>Prince de Condé. English</title>
            <author>Boursault, M. (Edme), 1638-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 172:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prince of Conde made English.</title>
                  <title>Prince de Condé. English</title>
                  <author>Boursault, M. (Edme), 1638-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 196 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Prince de Condé.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to M. Boursault. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Condé, Louis, --  prince de, 1530-1569 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRINCE OF Conde.</p>
            <p>Made Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Herringman,</hi> at the Anchor in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57675:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57675:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow far you will be pleaſed with this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of mine, I cannot reſolve, but this I can aſſure you, Perſons of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Quality and Parts have peruſed it with approbation.
<pb facs="tcp:57675:3"/>The great name that I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to give it, is ſufficient to juſtifie what I expoſe; for it is eaſily imaginable, that no Pen could be ſo imprudently audacious, as to place it in the Title of any Book that was defective, either in duty or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>Though in this little piece there are many Hiſtorical Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which may make it ſeem true, yet my deſign is
<pb facs="tcp:57675:3"/>not ſo much to delude, as to divert my Reader, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Error into which he would fall, ſhould he give too much faith to every particular in it.</p>
            <p>All the Paſſages of War, and Occurrences thereupon, are ſeriouſly true; but as to Love, and thoſe Myſtical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, I cannot ſecure you. To ſpeak properly, it is a new kind of <hi>Romance</hi> carried on
<pb facs="tcp:57675:4"/>under illuſtrious Names, to make it the more acceptable: For people have naturally more ſence and compaſſion for a Prince of their own knowledge, then for a <hi>Heroe,</hi> they never heard of before.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57675:4"/>
            <head>THE PRINCE OF <hi>CONDE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-50" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ove makes as many People unhappy, as Fortune: Many great Perſons have been ſeen to ſtruggle and bear up couragiouſly againſt the aſſaults of Fortune, who have not been able to withſtand the attacks and impreſſions of Love. A Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> (and that very name is ſufficient to pronounce him a great Man) had been the happieſt Prince of his time, had not that Paſſion mingled it ſelf with others, which made him ſo eminent; but his Ambition (which he cloaked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Religion) ceaſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57675:5"/>to be omnipotent, from the time that Love entered into his Heart. He was Brother to <hi>Anthony de Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> the Father of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, a Prince whoſe Memory is adorable in <hi>France,</hi> and whoſe Glory im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, whileſt there is the leaſt Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in the Age. This <hi>Anthony de Bourbon</hi> (King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> in right of his Wife <hi>Jeane d' Albert</hi>) was a Prince whoſe Courage wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly repoſed it ſelf, when there were no great Affairs on foot to give it agitation. His Prudence was but indifferent, and rather inclining to weakneſs, or to uſe the terms of the Hiſtorian, <hi>He was conſiderable more for his quality, then qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> But <hi>Lewis,</hi> his younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was valiant, firm, prompt, daring, and ſo poſſeſt of his own Merit, that he thought it a defect in his Fortune, more then in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, that he alſo had not a Crown.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57675:5"/>
               <p>He was very young when he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Eleanor de Roy,</hi> rather to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate his affairs (for his Birth was not attended with every thing neceſſary to his living up to it) then for any great inclination he had to her perſon: Not but ſhe was one of the handſomeſt about the Court, but in thoſe days their niceneſs began to be extravagant, and the Gallants by profeſſion (of which number the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was one) feared no ſcandal ſo much, as that of being kind to their Wives; vertue which they declared unfit to be practiſed by any perſon of condition. The Daughter of the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> (being as beautiful as her Father was valiant) was the Perſon the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> deſigned for his Conqueſt. This Mareſchal was devoted intirely to the Houſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> (which was a declared Enemy to the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi>) and had promiſed his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57675:6"/>Daughter to the eldeſt Son of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> againſt whom the Prince had too great an animoſity, not to ſeek out all ways imaginable to ingratiate with ſo fair a Lady, though but in revenge.</p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de S. Andre</hi>'s Daughter was one of the Maids of Honor to Queen <hi>Catharine,</hi> and not much loved by the reſt, becauſe her beauty was more celebrated; and there is nothing mortifying amongſt Ladies, like preference in that point: But the pleaſure which ſhe took to find her ſelf admired by all people that ſaw her, ſupported her well enough againſt their little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, and it was vengeance ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to leave them only ſuch hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, as ſhe had refuſed. <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, who Reigned at that time, repoſed his State Affairs upon the Queen-Mother, to whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being dearer then Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhe forgot nothing that might
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57675:6"/>keep him in ignorance; repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, that the life of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch was no longer then the life of another Man; that many times their prime was paſſed, before they underſtood how to imploy it to the beſt; and that the wiſdom of a young Prince conſiſted in taſting more pleaſure then the reſt of his Subjects. Poyſoned with theſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Maximes, he ſuffered no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to eſcape in which he might indulge, and the Queen upon her own private account was ſo unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that he ſhould want, that ſhe made it her buſineſs ſometimes to contrive entertainments for him her ſelf.</p>
               <p>One day after a hunting match in the Foreſt of <hi>Meudon</hi> (which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi>) the Queen having ſent the whole Court thither, would needs regal them at a Houſe which Monſieur <hi>Condé</hi> had at S. <hi>Cloud,</hi> and at that time was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57675:7"/>one of the pleaſanteſt places about <hi>Paris.</hi> The Maids of Honor of the two Queens (for <hi>Francis</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond had married <hi>Mary,</hi> Daughter and Heir of the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who delighted no more in State Matters then her Husband.) The Maids of Honor of theſe two Queens (I ſay) were dreſt with as much exactneſs as was poſſible, and did execution according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Beauty, wherewith each of them was charged; but among them all, there was none but Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſeille <hi>de S. André,</hi> univerſally admired; for ſhe captivated all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that preſented themſelves to her eye. The Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> who had no thoughts of courting her, but in oppoſition to the Prince <hi>de Joinville,</hi> to whom ſhe was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, began to acknowledge that he had done her injuſtice, and to find that upon her own ſcore, ſhe was ſufficiently amiable, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57675:7"/>other conſiderations. She was ſo great a lover of Fiſhing, that being come to S. <hi>Cloud,</hi> ſhe deſired one of the Queens Pages to procure her an Angle, what ever it coſt, and to expect her at the ſide of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Garden, whither ſhe would not fail to repair with all poſſible ſpeed. The great Feaſt that was preparing, was not ſo much to her ſatisfaction, as the pleaſure ſhe hoped to have after it was done. Leaſt ſhe ſhould be followed with a ſhole of admirers, with which ſhe was continually attended, ſhe went into the Chamber where the Queens were; and paſſing thorow it, went down privately, by a Pair of back Stairs, into the Garden to the Page, who was waiting for her, with her Rod and her Line.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> had never ſeen her ſo glorious as that day; and finding her much handſomer then ordinary, he began to love her
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57675:8"/>much better then before. He was diſcourſing in one of the Walks, with the Admiral of <hi>Colignes,</hi> to whom he diſcovered the Paſſion he had for that Lady, ſtopping his ears to what ever the ſaid Admiral could object againſt a thing that he found incompatible with their deſign, of wreſting the Government out of the hands of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe. What hath our deſign to do with my Paſſion</hi> (ſaid the Prince) <hi>the Religion of which, you are a Profeſſor, (and I, the rather, becauſe the</hi> Guiſes <hi>are of the other.) This Religion, I ſay, does it forbid any Man that is a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for loving the moſt beautiful Perſon in the World? Or what ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance would be left for me to take of the Prince of</hi> Joinville <hi>(whom I hate for being Son to the Duke of</hi> Guiſe) <hi>if, by a deſtiny tranſcending the good fortune of ſo many brave Men as are at Court, he ſhould engroſs ſo excellent a Lady. No, no, Monſieur
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57675:8"/>l'Admiral,</hi> ſaid the Prince, <hi>that ſhall never be laid at my door. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the</hi> Guiſes <hi>are not great enough to exempt their Family from a diſgrace, that perhaps neither you nor I am exempt from; and though I were not the moſt amorous of my Sex, it would pleaſe me to be ſo much their Enemy, as to give them all the diſquiet I might.</hi> He was in this diſcourſe when he perceived Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> marching towards the Canal, where ſhe was attended by the Page. <hi>Adieu Monſieur l' Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> (ſaid the Prince to him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſuddenly) <hi>it would be but civil, having brought you hither, to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you back; but the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture is, in my judgment, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent excuſe; and I ſhould deſerve that fortune which I am preparing for other people, if I ſhould ſuffer it to paſs without making my advantage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having made that ſhort Apology, he left the Admiral, and followed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57675:9"/>Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> but for fear ſhe ſhould be angry, he followed her another way, and never diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himſelf till ſhe had thrown in her Line two or three times. <hi>As far as I ſee, Madamoiſelle</hi> (ſaid he, falulting her) <hi>you are reſolved to give no quarter to any thing. After ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py an Hunting, I thought you would have ſuffered the poor Fiſh to have been at quiet, and contented your ſelf to have either killed or wounded what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever preſented it ſelf before your eyes. You are miſtaken Sir,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>if you think I have been ſo well pleaſed with this days Hunting; I have had a misfortune, that, perhaps, I might have repaired in this place, had not you interrupted me; and if you will, give me leave to be free, I must tell you, I am under a ſecret diſorder, that renders me almost inſenſible of the honor I receive by your preſence. The intelligence that I have had of your progreſs this day, Madam,</hi> (replied
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57675:9"/>the Prince) <hi>is perhaps better, and more certain then you imagine; though your Engins were unfervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, your beauty was not; the ſhot that came from your eyes, was more ſure then that which came from your hand, wounded more certainly, and in a more dangerous place.</hi> Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> having told the Page that there was no farther need of his attendance, and the Page be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone, <hi>I underſtand you Sir,</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Lady) <hi>and do ſee afar off, what is your deſign: The time of ſo great a Prince is too pretious to be abuſed. You love me? Yes Madam</hi> (replied the Prince) <hi>I do love you, and I love nothing in the World, with ſo much paſſion, as I love you. And where are your hopes?</hi> (ſaid ſhe to him) <hi>your heart is ingaged already to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam la Princeſs, and mine to the Prince</hi> de Joinville, <hi>who is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be my Husband. If my heart were ſo wholly ingaged to Madam la
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57675:10"/>Princeſs</hi> (replied the Prince) <hi>ſhe would not ſuffer you to have ſo much dominion there: And as to your heart, it is not yet obliged to the Husband, you are ſtill to marry, and which is more, you are too wiſe to permit that ever it be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is it, that I reſerve it for?</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Lady, interrupting him with an aſtoniſhment, that he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to regard) <hi>For me,</hi> (replied the Prince, with a confidence that redoubled her aſtoniſhment,) <hi>your heart is a prize impoſſible to be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but by a love as great as mine is for your Ladiſhip. The Husband (who I will not ſay is promiſed, for it is the worſt promiſe that can be made to you.) This Husband, I ſay, with whom you are threatned, does he know the value of the heart which your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reſerves for him? If he valued it, as it ought to be valued; would not be deſire to ow it to your ſelf, rather then to the Authority of your Father,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57675:10"/>who ſacrifices you to his particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest? The Prince of</hi> Joinville <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects you, ſince he hath thought himſelf ſure of you; and you need not doubt, but he will do it more when you are in his poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur le Prince</hi> (replied the young Lady, who had heard him with great patience) <hi>I thank you for your good counſel; you ſpeak to me like a true Enemy of the Family, from whence I am deſcended, and of that, to which I am deſigned. If you love me, as you pretend (and I am apt to think it poſſible, becauſe I am not altogether without allurements to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain you) I have advantage enough over you, to revenge Monſieur</hi> de Guiſe, <hi>and my Father, for the hatred which you bare them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe laſt words were delivered with an air, that gave the Prince to underſtand, his affairs were not in ſo good a poſture as he fancied; and the formality which ſhe uſed a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57675:11"/>while after, when ſhe took her leave of him, did perfectly diſabuſe him: He had preſaged much happineſs to his deſigns, from the eagerneſs wherewith ſhe demanded, whether he loved her? He uſed his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to have ſtaid her, but all was to no purpoſe; ſhe went back to the company that ſhe had left, and the Prince returned to the Admiral <hi>de Coligny,</hi> who was not a little pleaſed, that ſhe had ill treated a Paſſion which he had ſo little ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
               <p>The Evening being come, the Court returned to <hi>Paris;</hi> the Prince had another ſight of Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> in the <hi>Louvre;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored to accoſt her, but ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided the occaſion: As ſhe was getting from him, a Note tell out of her Pocket, which was taken up by the Prince, and the Lady never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it. He had not patience to ſtay till he got home, before he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57675:11"/>looked what was in it; he only went down out of the <hi>Louvre</hi> to read it more quietly, and by the light of a Lanthorne, at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Stairs, he found it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DO not fail to meet me about one a clock in the morning, in the Chamber of the Metamorphoſes; the Chamber where we paſſed the laſt night, is too near the Queens appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tement: And the fear I had to diſturb them, hindred me from taking my pleaſure as I would;</hi> La Noûe <hi>(with whoſe fidelity you are already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted) will take care the door ſhall be open.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This of the <hi>Metamorphoſes,</hi> was one of the richeſt Chambers in the <hi>Louvre;</hi> it was called <hi>The Chamber of the Metamorphoſes,</hi> becauſe every piece of the Tapiſtry hangings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented ſome of the diſguiſements,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57675:12"/>of which the gods made uſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their deſigns upon their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes; and the piece that carried the price from them all, was a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na made by ſo neat a hand, and drawn in ſo skilful a manner, that in her face one might ſee the very tranſport ſhe was in, when ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſhower of Gold.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriſed; he examined the hand, and looked it over and over, but could not gueſs whoſe it ſhould be: Had it not been ſo late, he would not have failed to have carried it to the Admiral, and deſired his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but it was almoſt midnight, and the rendezvous being at one, he had not time enough to do every thing he projected. As he went up again to the <hi>Louvre,</hi> he met <hi>Dande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot</hi> (Brother to the Admiral, and Colonel of the <hi>French</hi> Infantry) go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home: He deſired him, that he would not be far off, and that he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57675:12"/>would cauſe ſome of his Soldiers to ſtand to their Arms, and be ready to relieve him, if he ſhould happen to hear any noiſe. <hi>Dandelot</hi> preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to know what occaſion he had for them, and made ſome difficulty to leave him: But the Prince appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that a ſecond might fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his deſigns, conjured him to inquire no farther, proteſting, <hi>That the thing which he was ſo eager to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, was only matter of Love; and that if it were any thing of greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, he ſhould not be the Man from whom he would conceal it. It would much diſcompoſe me</hi> (replied <hi>Dandelot) if my zeal ſhould be an impediment to your good fortune. I am ſorry that I have detained you theſe few minutes, which you would have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed better elſwhere: To make you reparation, I will go and diſpoſe ſome of my Soldiers ſo near you, that they ſhall be ready to bring you off, if any Husband be ſo much an Enemy to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57675:13"/>State, as to interrupt the pleaſures of a Prince, who is ſo neceſſary to it.</hi> The Prince ſmiling at what <hi>Dandelot</hi> had ſaid, bowed his head, and went up into the <hi>Louvre,</hi> towards the appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tement, where the Chamber of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſes</hi> was. Whileſt he was in diſcourſe with <hi>Dandelot, La Noûe</hi> (who was the diſcreeteſt Woman in the whole Court, for the conduct of ſuch an intrigue) finding the hour of the Redezvous at hand, had been to put the Key privately into the Door, and was withdrawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to ſpare the fair Lady (to whom ſhe had done that great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) the ſhame of being ſeen in her paſſage.</p>
               <p>The Prince advanced to the Door, and found the Key in it; having ſcratched three or four times, and no body opening, he opened it himſelf, and ſtole in as ſoftly as he could. The Door ſhut with as lit-little noiſe as it opened; he drew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57675:13"/>his Sword out of his Belt, and with his hand felt over all the Chairs in the Chamber, to find whether any body was a ſleep there: When he had ſatisfied his curioſity, and could aſſure himſelf that he was alone, he moved towards that ſide where he knew the Bed ſtood, with deſign to hide himſelf under it, for he could not think of any other place where he might be ſo ſure; and the door of the Balliſters being locked, he paſſed over them.</p>
               <p>He was no ſooner ſettled under the Bed, but a Clock which he had in his Pocket, with an excellent Bell, began to ſtrike, and was near a quarter of an hour in ſtriking Twelve, which made him ſwear as many oaths, one after another. This was a new trouble to the Prince, who had taken no little pains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to lodge himſelf cloſe. His firſt thoughts were to throw it out of the Window, but the difficulty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57675:14"/>which he had paſſed to gain the Poſt he was in, remembring him of what he was like to find in getting out, and returning again, he pulled his Clock out of his Pocket, as well as he could, brake all the Springs, and put it up again when he had done. The time that was behind, would have ſeemed cruelly tedious to him, had he not imployed it in making reflections, ſome rational, and ſome amorous. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Bed! he thought it was but an odd place for ſo great a Perſon; and his heart as well as his quality, was much offended at what his love had put him upon; but then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he recollected, and perſwaded himſelf, That his reputation was at too high a pitch to be leſſened by any thing; that no poſture was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent, which was uſeful; that the Gallant he endeavored to ſurpriſe, might poſſibly prove the greateſt of his Enemies, and it would be a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57675:14"/>ſhame to him, if ſcruple (which is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the pretence of mean ſpirits) ſhould make him loſe ſo fair an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to revenge himſelf. From theſe, he paſſed to other reflections; he doubted not, but it was Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> to whom his Note was directed; but his great trouble was to think who it ſhould come from: He ſaw plainly by the appartment which they had choſen, that it was ſome perſon of quality who had good intereſt at Court; and the appartment of the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> cheif Miniſter of State (to whom he was a mortal Enemy) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not far from the appointed Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous, he could not but think ſometimes it might be he. The firſt voice that he heard, was Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de S. Andrés,</hi> with that he was no much ſupriſed, but not long after, he heard another that ſtartled him exceedingly.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57675:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, though young, had eyes like other men; and the Charms of Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> had not eſcaped them: It was he who had given order that Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> ſhould be there, and committed it to Madam <hi>de la Noûe</hi> to give her notice; and ſhe had cauſed that Note to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by one of her Maids, ſo expert in the profeſſion of her Miſtreſs, that her ingenuity was recompenced afterwards with a Priory of 5 or 6000 livers <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince diſplayed in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner under the Bed, diverted himſelf very ill, and had put by the Bed-cloaths towards the Head, to give himſelf more air, and that he might the better underſtand what his Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants would ſay when they met; but he quickly pulled them down again, when he heard the Kings voice; and great terrors were upon him, for fear he ſhould be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57675:15"/>It was ſupected, that he would, by force, endeavor to poſſeſs himſelf of the Government, and herhaps that ſuſpicion was but juſt: Had he been found concealed ſo near the Perſon of the King, at ſo unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an hour, with his Sword out of his Belt, his Enemies would have miſinterpreted his deſign, and of an amorous intrigue, have made a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital offence: To which, the Note which he had taken up, would not have added a little. By that it would have appeared, that he knew where the King was to be at that time alone, and without defence; and the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> to whom he gave great jealouſie, would not have failed to have ſaid, that it was a place very proper to execute the worſt deſigns that he had.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations running in his mind, his diſcretion began to appear in the releif of his Love; but it was ſomething too late. He
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57675:16"/>repented that he had ſo raſhly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged himſelf in an affair, that, for ought he knew, might have very ill conſequences; and whileſt he was under this confuſion, the King and Madamoiſelle were undreſſed, and had doubtleſs given very good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the love they had one for the other, had they not been inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by an alarm that obliged them to put off their expreſſions till another time.</p>
               <p>The Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was three moneths gone with child; ſhe was of a very tender Complexion, and the exerciſe which ſhe had uſed in that days hunting, had diſordered her much, to the affliction of all thoſe who were pleaſed ſhe was breeding. The noiſe of her pains, quickly went thorow the <hi>Louvre;</hi> the <hi>Valet de Chamber</hi> who was in waiting that night, and had the honor to be intruſted with the Kings amors, came immediately to give
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57675:16"/>him notice. The King was half un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, and being angry to have loſt ſo fair an occaſion, was much troubled at the condition of the Queen; but for fear of being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré,</hi> it was neceſſary (againſt all common practice) to leave the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs for the Wife; and lay aſide the tranſports of a Lover, to ſhow the complacency of a Husband.</p>
               <p>The Queen miſcarried, for which, ſome were glad, and others were ſorry; for the Court was divided.</p>
               <p>This accident, that bred an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal diſorder in the reſt of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> was a great calm to the mind of the Prince. They had no ſooner advertiſed his Majeſty of the condition of the Queen, but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired with all diligence into his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> into hers; whether ſhe was attended by the officious Matron Madam <hi>de la Noûe,</hi> who took no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57675:17"/>care of locking the Door after her, as a thing of little importance.</p>
               <p>The Prince being left in this manner Maſter of the Field, was not long in making his way out; proteſting never to run himſelf into the like danger again, at leaſt, whileſt he had the uſe of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Paſſing thorow an Entry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Kings Antichamber, he met his Majeſty as he was going to the Queens appartment; the King asked him what he did in the <hi>Louvre</hi> ſo late with ſo much care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his countenance. He had a ready wit, and anſwered him preſently, That he came from play; that he had loſt a conſiderable ſum of Money; and, that the news of the Queens indiſpoſition having been uſed as a pretence to give off, by the perſons with whom he was at play, he was going home to his Lodgings in the diſorder his Majeſty obſerved. It was happy for him, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57675:17"/>King queſtioned him no farther; had he ſtaid above never ſo little longer, he had been certainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. <hi>Dandelot</hi> in purſuance of his promiſe, had commanded ſome of his Soldiers to be upon the Guard, who, upon the noiſe which was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the Queens indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ran to the releif of the Prince, and were already upon the Stairs; when his name being much in their Mouths, his preſence cauſed them very ſeaſonably to be ſilent. He went immediately out of the <hi>Louvre</hi> in the company of <hi>Dandelot,</hi> to whom he promiſed to meet about ten of the clock, at the Lodgings of his Brother, the Admiral of <hi>Coligny;</hi> where if he met him, he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part a ſecret to him, that he would not be at all troubled to hear.</p>
               <p>His impatience to ſee the Admiral, was too great to fail at the appointed hour: <hi>Dandelot</hi> was a great lover of Secreta, and had prevented him.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57675:18"/>
                  <hi>Ah! dear Coſin,</hi> cryed the Prince, when he came near the Admiral, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Man in the World, under the greateſt aſtoniſhment! all that I have ſeen hitherto in my life, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to what I am going to tell you: In a word, it is a thing ſo incredible, that when I have told you, if you do not believe me, I ſhall pardon you.</hi> S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré <hi>(I mean not the Mareſchals Lady, for I believe her much wiſer) but the Queens Maid of Honor, is of ſo tryed and tractable a vertue, that the Prince</hi> de Joinville, <hi>if he marries her, can teach her nothing that is new. But this is not that</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that is ſo ſtrange, She is fair, ſhe is among the great People, where example gives ſome kind of Authority; ſhe is not full ſixteen years of age, about which time, the honor of young Ladies begin to totter: Few there are that can hold out continent ſo long, and common ſence will not ſuffer us to be amazed at any thing that Cuſtome has made
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57675:18"/>familiar. But Coſin, this is it that will ſurpriſe you, you will never be able to gueſs at the Gallant. Run over the whole Court, caſt your eyes upon all the Gallants in the Town, you ſhall name fifty, and I will lay you a wager you miſs him. This circumſtantial deſcription that he gave of Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle</hi> de S. Andrés <hi>Gallant, made them that they could not fix it upon any of that ſort at Court; but the Admiral and his Brother began to imagine it ſome old venerable Abbot, whoſe love was not ſo pleaſant as profitable: For the young Lady was rich only in her Beauty, and therefore they named the Cardinal of</hi> Tournon, Bertrandi <hi>(who had been Keeper of the Seals,) the Chancellor</hi> Oliver, <hi>the Seigneur</hi> de Pybrac, <hi>and ſome others of that ſort. No</hi> (ſaid the Prince) <hi>if you conſider his quality, he is above all theſe, but if you conſider his gallantry, he is much beneath them. Madamoiſelle</hi> de S. André <hi>is beloved by the King,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57675:19"/>of which, the laſt night I had like to have had an incontestable evidence. Then he gave them an account of all that had hapned, and ſhewed them the Note which had given him ſo ſtrange an alarm. This Note was of mighty uſe to their deſign; they had thoughts of breaking the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Mareſchal</hi> de S. André, <hi>and the Duke of</hi> Guiſe, <hi>and the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible way to ſucceed, was to ruine the reputation of Madamoiſelle</hi> de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré, <hi>and make the Prince</hi> de Joinville <hi>to deſert her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dandelot,</hi> being perſwaded that Madam l'Admiral had more cunning and malice, then all three of them put together, was of opinion, that ſhe ſhould be conſulted. She was ſo true a Hugenot, and had ſo great zeal of the honor of her Religion, that for the ſervice of God, there was no injuſtice in the World, that ſhe would have ſcrupled to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; they ſent to her to come to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57675:19"/>them, but ſhe was at Prayers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind her Bed, and could not come immediately: As ſoon as ſhe had done, ſhe appeared, and the Prince having told her what he had told before to her Husband, he would have ſhown her the Note, but ſhe would not by any means. <hi>It will be enough</hi> (ſaid ſhe to him) <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the reputation of</hi> S. André, <hi>if you pleaſe but to read it to me. After dinner I will take an opportunity to ſhow it to the Queen, and ſwear a thouſand horrible oaths that I never ſo much as read it: If I ſhould read it my ſelf, I could not ſwear with that freedom, for I would not wound my Conſcience for a Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Admiral liked the expedient very well: <hi>Dandelot</hi> not only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired the wit of his Siſter in Law, but applauded her probity: The Prince who hated Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> as much as he had formerly loved her, and deſired to revenge
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57675:20"/>himſelf of the affront (as he thought) which ſhe had done him, in loving the King, delivered his Note to Madam l'Admiral, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make good uſe of it. The Afternoon was long a coming, at leaſt, in the opinion of Madam l'Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral. She was that day at the <hi>Louvre</hi> in very good time, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got not the Billet which the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> had given her. The young Queen was not allowed to ſee any body, by reaſon of what ſhe had endured the night before; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King contented himſelf with his title, without doing the drudgery; people did not addreſs ſo ſolemnly to him, as to the Queen-Mother. Whileſt the Queen was at dinner, three young Virgins were preſented to her, the Daughters of a <hi>Primiere Preſidente</hi> of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Roûen,</hi> which the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident had brought forth at a Birth. They were all very fair, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57675:20"/>alike, not only in the features of their face; but in their ſhape, hair, geſtures, and voice, that they were forced to put them into ſeveral habits to diſtinguiſh them.</p>
               <p>The whole Court was in the Queens Chamber, admiring the ſtrange reſemblance of theſe three Children, when Madam l'Admiral came in, ſhe was ſo taken (as the reſt were) with the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narineſs of the thing, that ſhe forgot (at leaſt, for ſometime) her deſigns againſt Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André.</hi> Looking upon the young Maidens with too much intention, ſhe drew ſomething out of her Pocket, and had the ſame misfortune which the Lady had, whom ſhe was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy.</p>
               <p>The Note wherewith the Prince had intruſted her, fell out of her Pocket, and ſhe never perceived it. The Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> being next her, and ſeeing it fall, caſt his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57675:21"/>upon it very neatly, and, without much trouble, took them up together. He was as impatient to be peeping, as the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> had been the night before: He ſtole out of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> read it, and was infinitely ſurpriſed to find Madam l'Admiral (who had formerly been very handſome, but not young theſe nine or ten years) ſhould have a rendezvous of this nature; for he did not heſitate one moment to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that it was ſhe to whom the Ticket was addreſſed.</p>
               <p>The three young Virgins of <hi>Roûen,</hi> having taken their leaves of the Queen, Madam l'Admiral be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to remember her ſelf of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that brought her to the <hi>Louvre,</hi> and that ſhe had a fair opportunity to put it in execution. She felt for her Ticket, but it was not to be found; ſhe felt and felt for it with great diligence, but to no purpoſe: She was ſo cruelly diſturbed at the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57675:21"/>loſs of it, that foreſeeing, it would be impoſſible to conceal it, ſhe went home to her Lodgings, where, with meer vexation, ſhe fell ſick all that day, and had, perhaps, been ſo long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, had not the ſame thing cured, that wounded her, as the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will diſcover.</p>
               <p>Whileſt ſhe was complaining of the Heavens, that they had not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted her to accompliſh her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous deſigns: The Prince <hi>de Joinville,</hi> who knew her Father the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> ſuffered nothing to paſs, that might do the Admiral a prejudice, carried him the Billet, which he was ſure would be very welcome. The Duke asked his Son if he did not miſtake, and if he was fure that the Note belonged to Madam l'Admiral? The Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> having aſſured him, that nothing was more certain; they went together to the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who was in the company
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57675:22"/>of the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Articles of Marriage (which was to be conſummated in few days) that they might be carried next morning to the King, and the two Queens, who would do them the honor to ſign them.</p>
               <p>This Cardinal was a very danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Enemy. When he found oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deſtroy any Man that he hated, he never neglected it: And finding himſelf now, as he thought, Maſter of the Reputation of Madam l'Admiral (whom he called <hi>The ſworn Enemy of the Church,)</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he ſhould have betrayed the Office of a Cardinal, if he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred her ruine but one moment. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de S. André,</hi> applauded his Eminences ſentiment, as very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and altogether recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> to be ſilent, eſpecially (ſaid the Cardinal) to your Miſtreſs; and if you have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57675:22"/>not power to contain, forbear rather to ſee her: She is young, and a Woman; both of which are incompatible with a ſecret. The Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> promiſed what they deſired, and was as good as his word.</p>
               <p>During the time that this unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Ticket went from one Enemy to another, giving as much vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Colignies,</hi> as it did plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the <hi>Guiſes:</hi> The King being willing to recover what he loſt the night before by the Queens indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, gave order to Madam <hi>de la Noûe</hi> (who was always ready at his Majeſties ſervice) to renew the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that was interrupted, and cauſe his Miſtreſs to meet him again at the old Rendezvous, as ſoon as the clock ſhould ſtrike twelve.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine</hi> (who knew that Queen <hi>Catherine</hi> had a mortal hatred for Madam l'Admiral, as one who had been always inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57675:23"/>with the Dutcheſs of <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> the Miſtreſs of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, went to wait upon her, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, that he might have the honor to ſpeak with her in her Cloſet, and there to ſhew her the Billet which the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> his Nephew had ſo dexterouſly taken up. <hi>Ah! inſatiable</hi> (cried the Queen, when ſhe had read it her ſelf) <hi>whileſt ſhe was young, it was no wonder ſhe was court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Mareſchal</hi> Stroſſy, <hi>and I never condemned her. Every one knows Madam</hi> (replied the Cardinal) <hi>that youth will not laſt always, and your Majeſty was always too diſcreet to oppoſe your ſelf againſt any thing that is permitted; for Courtſhip is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or forbidden according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent times, in which they are pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed. In the time of the late King, the vertuous Ladies of the Court had each of them ſome honeſt Gentleman, or other, with whom they carried on that commerce of Gallantry; and this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57675:23"/>the old Ladies did as well as the young, when their beauty began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, or they had means to ſupply the want of it, by their bounty to their Court-Lovers, who perhaps had no other Revenue but their</hi> bonne mine. <hi>But under the Government of your Majeſty (to whom the State is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely obliged for your care and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citouſneſs to reform it) it would be indecent to ſuffer this licentiouſneſs, and leave the obſcenities of Madam l'Admiral, or the profanation of the place unpuniſhed. I am not the only perſon Madam</hi> (continued the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal) <hi>who looks with indignation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inſolence which ſhe would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in a place where Mediocrity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is a kind of a crime. My Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of</hi> Guiſe <hi>(and you know Madam, how dear your Majeſties honor is to him; and whether Heaven it ſelf can produce a Man with greater zeal then that which he has for your intereſt.) My Brother of</hi> Guiſe <hi>(I ſay) and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57675:24"/>the Mareſchal</hi> de S. André <hi>(the next perſon to my Brother for his devotion to your Majeſty, in your whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) are infinitely ſcandaliſed at this impudence; and do attend what your Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to command them.</hi> The Queen when ſhe had given the Cardinal freedom to ſpeak what he pleaſed, replied, That ſhe was of his judgment; that this inſolence was too criminal to paſs unpuniſhed, and asked him, what expedient he could think of, to convince the Admirals Lady of a crime which would be ſo eaſie for her to deny. <hi>I beg your Majeſties pardon</hi> (replied the Cardinal) <hi>if I ſully your imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with a figure that may perhaps intrench upon your modeſty: I know what you will ſuffer, to hear me ſay it is impoſſible to convict her, unleſs ſhe be taken in the act: But there are few terms to expreſs any thing that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, that do not carry ſomething of immodesty along with them; and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57675:24"/>bluſh that riſes already in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties face, gives no little luſtre to your Majeſties vertue.</hi> At length the Queen conſented abſolutely to what the Cardinal deſired: She had an old pique to Madam l'Admiral, which ſhe was very glad to ſatisfie ſo eaſily. And though her authority over the Kings mind was very great, yet becauſe he was natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wavering and inconſtant: The Cardinal begged of her Majeſty, that ſhe would preſerve it as a ſecret from him, telling her, that her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle advice was ſufficient to warrant what they intended to do.</p>
               <p>Twelve a clock came, and ſeveral people were waiting, upon ſeveral deſigns. The Queen could not think of ſleeping, till ſhe had had the pleaſure of underſtanding the confuſion of the Admirals Lady, and who was her Gallant. She had ſeen the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> after the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine</hi> went away,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57675:25"/>and he had with a great deal of readineſs obliged himſelf to give her an account of whatever hapned in that buſineſs; the Queen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be punctual, and promiſed to ſit up till he came. She imployed her ſelf, in the mean time, in reading, and had kept only two of the Ladies of her Bed-chamber with her, her Maids of Honor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone to their Chambers as ſoon as the clock ſtruck twelve, as was the uſual cuſtome: And Madam <hi>de la Noûe</hi> having advertiſed Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> of the hour which the King had appointed, ſhe bad her companions good night, and for faſhion-ſake entring into her own Lodgings, ſtole out again pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after to go into the Chamber of the Metamorphoſes, where ſhe ſtaid not long before the King came in.</p>
               <p>The hearts of the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> were too
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57675:25"/>ſtreight to contain the joy that they conceived; they ſtaid at Supper the Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> and promiſed them ſuch a treat as they could not expect. Twelve a clock ſtruck, and they heard nothing of the treat; the Princes called for it, but were deſired to be patient, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that if they waited three nights together, it would be well worth their attendance when it came. The Rendezvous this night was appointed preciſely at twelve a clock; but that which was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Note, which Madam l'Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral had loſt, was not till one; and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de S. André,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> (who thought themſelves highly ingaged to their fortune, which had preſented them with an occaſion of diſgracing the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of their Enemies) would have believed themſelves guilty of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57675:26"/>an irrepairable fault, if they had been deficient in any thing that might have haſtned his ruine. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had placed a Spie, where it was impoſſible any body ſhould enter into the Room of the Metamorphoſes, without being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: The Duke was aſſured of his fidelity, and told him, That a Gallant had appointed a Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to his Miſtreſs in that place, but he told him not any thing who they were. He promiſed him great rewards, and conjured him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve very diligently, and not to ſtir till he ſent him word by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who for a ſignal ſhould demand the Diamond that he had left with him. The Spie wanted no wit, and underſtood well enough that the imployment which was given him, was one of the ways by which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were advanced moſt eaſily at Court; he promiſed the Duke to be punctual in all that he deſired.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57675:26"/>Things being in this poſture, the the clock ſtruck one. The Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de S. André</hi> perſwaded the Duke, that men did not meet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways exactly at the hour appointed; that their deſign would infallibly miſcarry, if it ſhould be their ill fortune to execute it but one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment too ſoon; and therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to protract another half hour, and they ſhould ſurpriſe the Admirals Lady in the height of her delight. About half an hour paſt one, a perſon was ſent to the Scout, to demand the Diamond which the Duke left with him, which was the ſignal, upon which word was to be ſent, whether the lovers were come, or not. The Scout replied, That they were come long ſince, and the Meſſenger ran immediately with the news to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57675:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>COme Gentlemen, the hour of your entertainment is now come,</hi> ſaid the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> to the Duke <hi>de Montpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon; it has been long a coming it is true, but it is well worth your attendance; and if ever you had occaſion to laugh heartily in your whole lives, I dare promiſe it will be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: For my own part</hi> (ſaid he, with a torrent of joy that endeavored to expand it ſelf) <hi>I must tell you, I would not change the pleaſure of this night, for the beſt days pleaſure in my whole life: And if ever I had any true delight, it is that which I am now going to receive, and you to be my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To give them a taſte of it before hand, he told them in few words what it was; the ſecret being no longer of conſequence, ſeeing the execution was ſo near; whereupon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57675:27"/>he ſhewed them the Note which fell into the hands of the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> (who by way of intimacy, he called already his Son in Law, becauſe his Marriage with the ſaid Mareſchals Daughter, as I have ſaid before, was to be conſummate in a few days.)</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing young Gentlemen, and lovers of diverſion, were highly tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ingaged in ſuch an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; propoſed infinite ſatisfaction to themſelves in ſeeing and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the looks of Madam l'Admiral in ſo mortifying a conjuncture, and in diſcovering her Gallant. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> took each of them a Lamp in their hands, and followed by the two Princes (whom they had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to treat) they ſtole as ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they could to the door of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57675:28"/>Chamber of the Metamorphoſes. The Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine</hi> knew a great part of the revenge would conſiſt in his being preſent, when Madam l'Admiral was ſurpriſed, but his Character would not permit him to bear them company. They liſtned for ſome time at the door, but heard nothing; the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little, and a Groom of the Chamber, who was left there, and ſuppoſed it to be Madam <hi>de la Noûe,</hi> coming according to her cuſtome to fetch Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> at a certain hour to her Chamber, he opened the door. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> told him, That he underſtood very well what was in agitation, and was privy to the ſecret: The Valet apprehending the Duke might have ſome buſineſs of importance with his Majeſty, ſuffered him to enter, and all his retinue.</p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt ſcrupulous, was the firſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57675:28"/>who advanced to the Bed ſide, and ſtood ſtill as amazed and immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able when he ſaw the King on one ſide, and on the other his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, looking better then he had ever ſeen her in his life. By reaſon of the warmth of the weather, her arms were out of Bed, her neck naked, and her little new ſwelling breſts ſo white, and repreſented the pretty red nipples, wherewith Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had embelliſhed them ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fomely, that it was impoſſible to ſee any thing more tender and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching.</p>
               <p>This ſurpriſe in the Mareſchal, cauſed the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to come forward, and after him the Prince <hi>de Joinville,</hi> and the two Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> in their turns. All of them were ſtrangely aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee the King on one ſide of the Bed, and Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> on the other, both of them aſleep with the ſame quiet and ſecurity, as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57675:29"/>if they had been Man and Wife: But though the aſtoniſhment was univerſal, it was in a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The Father, Father in Law, and Lover, were in great conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> finding their entertainment much pleaſanter then was promiſed, were forced to take all imaginable pains to keep themſelves from laughing right out; and indeed it was well for the Mareſchal, that his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Breſts were ſo naked to take up their thoughts; otherwiſe, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in which he was, would have made any man laugh, though he had been never ſo ſerious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-100" type="pages">
               <p>Whileſt ſome of them were mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally troubled, and the reſt ſo well pleaſed, that it is not eaſie to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: The light glaring upon the eyes of Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré,</hi> awakened her; ſhe rubbed them a while, opened them when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57675:29"/>ſhe had done; and the firſt thing ſhe looked upon, being her Father, ſhe fetched a skreek that wakned the King; and I do not doubt, but he was as much ſurpriſed, as other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but his ſurpriſe being over, his love inſpired him with more wit, and more courage then he had ever diſcovered before. Having endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored to encourage and comfort Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> (who was weeping) by promiſing to take her into his protection; he demanded of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the reſt that were with him, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they durſt preſume to enter, at ſuch an hour, into a place where they knew he was taking his repoſe. The Mareſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That had they known his Majeſty had been there, they would not have preſumed to interrupt him; and that for his own part, he expected nothing leſs then what he had found: That it was he who
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57675:30"/>had ſtaid the Duke of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> to give them a divertiſement, in which he little thought his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould have born apart. That could he have preſaged, or been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the honor his Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon his family, he ſhould have had more diſcretion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, then to have brought ſo many witneſſes; and having ſaid ſo, he withdrew.</p>
               <p>The King perceiving the preſence of ſo many Princes, and eſpecially the Prince <hi>de Joinville,</hi> was a great trouble to Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> he commanded them to retire, and they obeyed his command. When they were gone, he applied what conſolation he could, and perhaps better then he could do in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of her Father. He called for the Groom of his Chamber, by whoſe indiſcretion they were let in; but the Kings anger, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelles
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57675:30"/>tears having given him to underſtand the fault that he had committed, he was afraid of being puniſhed, and had made his eſcape: But the Governneſs, Madam <hi>de la Noûe</hi> coming in, in the nick, ſhe lighted the King to his Chamber, and when ſhe had done, came back to do as much for the Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle.</p>
               <p>The Queen Mother (to whom the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> had promiſed to give an account of all that he ſhould ſee) was naturally impatient; and the clock having ſtruck two, and no news of her Prince, ſhe fent to look him, by one of her Maids of Honor, in the appartment of his Uncle the Cardinal; he came to wait upon her with a countenance as chearful as the nature of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture would permit. <hi>Prince</hi> de Joinville (ſaid her Majeſty to him, as ſoon as he was near her) <hi>I do not ask after the greatneſs of her confuſion,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57675:31"/>or whether Madam l'Admiral is not almost diſtracted: I do not doubt but ſhe is highly ſenſible of the affront, and will move Heaven and Earth to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged: I paſs all that by, and only deſire to know who was her Gallant. What is he? Is he young? Is he hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome? Is he of any conſiderable qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? How did the Lady like him? Tell me, in ſhort, and give me a true deſcription, eſpecially how he looked and behaved himſelf when he was taken. What interrogatories were theſe for the Prince</hi> de Joinville, <hi>who was moſt deſperately in love with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle</hi> de S. Andre? He replied (with a diſcompoſure that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be excuſed) <hi>That the Gallant her Majeſty deſired ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, was very young: That as to his perſon, thoſe who delighted not in tall, lusty men, would think him handſome enough; and for his quality, he must needs ſay it was very conſiderable: That the Lady, was doubtleſty, very
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57675:31"/>well pleaſed, and would be much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by the rest, when her good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was known: That as to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment and looks, when he was taken, it was ſomething more fierce then at other times; and that inſtead of being terrified himſelf, he made his ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to tremble. This Madam is a relation which your Majesty has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to give; let me beg of you to inquire no farther. To morrow your Ears will be clogged with what I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to tell you; and if your Majeſty underſtood with what regret and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I have gone thus far, you would admire my patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queen thought he had been ill, and ſuffered him to retire; he returned into his Uncles appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and found him ſtorming like mad. The Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> were got by themſelves, to laugh and make ſport at the afflictions of the reſt; the only trouble they had,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57675:32"/>was to think all the World was in Bed, and they were forced to ſtay till next morning, before they could publiſh what they knew.</p>
               <p>They went late to Bed, but got up very early, being impatient to let the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> know upon what account the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> had detained them at Supper, and the end and Cataſtrophe of their deſign.</p>
               <p>Though the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and they, were of two contrary Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and even of contrary parties; yet they had great eſteem for one another, eſpecially the Prince <hi>de la Roche-ſur-Yon,</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Montpenſier,</hi> for the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> upon whom they looked, as upon the braveſt man of his time. The joy wherewith the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> underſtood the confuſion of the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> revenged him in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the troubles which the loſs of the Billet had given him before.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57675:32"/>Nothing could be more pleaſant, then to imagine the pains which they had occaſioned, by their own conduct and eager proſecution of that intrigue, and by the detention of two perſons of their quality, to give them ſuch an extraordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale. The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> liked the divertiſement too well to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs it to himſelf: He would have been very unwilling the Admiral ſhould have had it from any body but him; and therefore fearing he might be too late, that ſome other perſon might prevent him; and that his information ſhould not be the firſt, he repaired to his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with all diligence. The Admiral was no ſooner acquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but he ran immediately into his Wives Chamber; ſhe had been ill all night of the loſs of her Billet, and was to be let blood that morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But the tidings which the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral brought her, ſaved her Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57675:33"/>a labor, and made a ſpeedier cure then phlebotomy would have done. Sick, or not ſick, Madam l'Admiral got up, called for her Coach, told it to every body ſhe met, and they being as liberal of it as ſhe, in a very ſhort time the news was known all over the Town. The Kingdom, at that time, was under great agitation, by reaſon of the differences betwixt the Catholicks, and the Hugonots, who under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Reformation, did exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly rend and diſtract it. There were ſome perſons who that morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had made a Song of the ſtate of the Kings affairs, and were ſinging it (but very low) as his Majeſty was riſing; it was ſet to the tune of a Ballad that was then in mighty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and the words were theſe.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas fair Nymph, do you not think't a thing</l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:57675:33"/>
                        <l>Of dangerous conſequence t' abuſe your Charms.</l>
                        <l>The Throne is tottering, yet the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King</l>
                        <l>Repoſes gently in your tender Arms.</l>
                        <l>Ah that (to calm our ſpirits) we might ſee</l>
                        <l>The State as quiet, and as ſnug as he.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Queen her ſelf, lies not more cloſe then you,</l>
                        <l>Nor ſleeps more ſweetly by the Royal ſide;</l>
                        <l>You ne'er concern your thoughts, nor curl your brow,</l>
                        <l>At Proteſtants or Papiſts Plots or Pride:</l>
                        <l>Ah that (for th'common good) our State did know,</l>
                        <l>But half that Peace, half that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as you.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>What is commonly ſung about the ſtreets, or once put into a Song,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57675:34"/>ceaſes to be a Secret; nor was it long before the Queen was better informed of what the Prince <hi>de Joinville</hi> gave her but an imperfect relation. Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> had been always conſtant in her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance before, and not daring to appear that morning, ſhe confirmed what began to be publick. The Queen ſent for her, but the Kings Phyſitian (called <hi>Miron</hi>) was with Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> and had orders to ſay, That ſhe was ill; which at another time would have been a lawful excuſe; but as things then ſtood, it was rather an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her guilt; and her Majeſty (who was not eaſily deluded) gueſt unhappily at the truth. She was highly incenſed, and could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain her ſelf; ſhe ſent to deſire the King to come to her, the King came, and they went together into her Cloſſet, where ſhe began to reprove him ſeverely, and in a tone that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57675:34"/>might have made him tremble: But the King being prepared by his Love and his Miſtreſs, interrupted her at the very firſt volley, and that with an aſſurance and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence beyond her expectation. He told her, it was true indeed, he had a kindneſs for the perſon ſhe named, and he deſired ſhe would give him leave to entertain himſelf with her, or elſe ſurrender his authority, that he might imploy himſelf otherwiſe: He remembred the Queen, that her power was of no longer duration then he pleaſed; that if ſhe croſſed him in his love, he would not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge her in her ambition; and that (without violence to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which he ought her, as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) when ever he did but ſay he would be King, ſhe muſt ceaſe to be Queen.</p>
               <p>Theſe words ſhe had reaſon to believe were none of her Sons; yet ſeeing Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:57675:35"/>ſpake them by his mouth, ſhe had as much reaſon to be aſtoniſhed, as if they had been his own. She durſt not purſue the expoſtulation, nor drive the buſineſs any farther, leaſt Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> ſhould furniſh him with another anſwer. The King was miſtaken to think that the Queen had a deſign to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his divertiſements; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, her thoughts were taken up, how ſhe might entertain him perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually; and had Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> been only handſome, the Queen had been the firſt that would have recommended her, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded his choice: But Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> had Wit as well as Beauty; and a Head that was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to keep the Queen-Mother upon her guard; for ſhe apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when Madamoiſelle came once to be Miſtreſs of the Kings heart, ſhe would make him ſenſible, how much he was abuſed. Upon
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57675:35"/>which conſideration, all was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated before they parted; the King kept his Miſtreſs, and the Mother the Government.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> could not forget the great favors which he had received of their Majeſties; and his gratitude was ſuch, that he would not ſuffer his Son to intrench upon the reſpect which he ought to the King ſo far, as to continue his rival. The Articles of Marriage which the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> had drawn up, were cancelled and torn, and the Government of <hi>Lions</hi> (that was then vacant) being conferred upon the Mareſchal, every one was contented, or at leaſt they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. Andre</hi> was looked upon as the Kings Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and reſpected beyond what ſhe was formerly; the Queen-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was afraid of her, and though ſhe could not behold her without
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57675:36"/>indignation, yet ſhe thought it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion to conceal it; and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> if any troubles were upon her on that account (as it is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there were) ſhe alſo kept them to her ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> obſerving all parties ſo well contented, was much diſcontented himſelf, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to prevail with Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> to love him, he reſolved ſhe ſhould hate him. He watched his opportunity when the King was abſent, made her a viſit in her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and complemented her ſlily upon her late advancement: She took it for an affront, as ſhe had reaſon, and anſwered him very quick and loud, That that was one of the Reaſons which had kept her from admitting his paſſion; for ſhe had conſidered, and thought it more honorable to be a Kings Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, then Miſtreſs to a younger Brother of the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:57675:36"/>who had nothing to truſt to, but his Sword. <hi>And Madamoiſelle or Madam</hi> (<hi>for now I know not by which of them to call you,</hi> replied the Prince) <hi>I loved you too well to let your great honor be loſt in obſcurity: It is to your own Charms you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted for your dignity, but it was to me you were beholding for the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I could not endure you ſhould be any longer deprived of thoſe reſpects, which that great happineſs would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you; had it not been for me (who took inconceivable pains to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the truth) the World had been ſtill ignorant of your preferment, it is to me you are indebted for the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication:</hi> And ſo far was he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with ſeverity, that leaſt ſhe ſhould not yet underſtand what he meant, he told her in expreſs terms, That at her return from S. <hi>Cloud,</hi> it was he who had found the Note that ſhe had dropped; that at one a clock at night, he had conveyed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57675:37"/>himſelf into her Alcove, and been a ſpectator of the joy and alacrity, wherewith ſhe undreſſed her ſelf, when as ill luck would have it, all her hopes were defeated by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of the Queen. In ſhort, he omitted nothing that he thought might provoke her to hate him, and he ſucceeded ſo well, that from that time ſhe hated him mortally.</p>
               <p>The Prince made Courtſhip elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré</hi> kept to her King, and did very well. The firſt viſit the King made her, ſhe made her complaints of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and repreſented his deportment ſo hainous, that the King could not but be ſo far ſenſible, as to eſpouſe her quarrel, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge it. Whileſt they were imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſearching an opportunity, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince made new addreſſes to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of the Maids of Honor called Madamoiſelle <hi>de Limevil,</hi> a young Lady not altogether ſo beautiful as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57675:37"/>Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> but kinder and leſs proud: And indeed he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf ſo effectually to her, that he arrived at that which is the end of moſt Courtſhip. She had by him a Son, which was born under the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Nineth, the twenty fifth of <hi>May,</hi> One thouſand five hundred ſixty one, and in the very <hi>Louvre;</hi> but the Queen, who at that time had need of the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> to balance the power of the houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> that was grown too haughty, connived at her frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>The inclination which the Prince had to Madamoiſelle <hi>de Limevil</hi> laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not long, but rather becauſe the affairs of State had changed their face, then any diſguſt that ſhe gave him. In the mean time, the King was highly offended at his behavior with Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André;</hi> had ſworn his ruine, and that he might be as good as his word, he ſided
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57675:38"/>with the <hi>Guiſes:</hi> The Prince was called but very ſeldom to Council, though in Juſtice he was to have been the firſt in rank, yet he found the <hi>Guiſes</hi> ſet before him, by the Kings expreſs order, and the ſame contempt that inhanced the hearts of his enemies, troubled him exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
               <p>The Hereſie which <hi>Luther</hi> had diffuſed all over <hi>Europe,</hi> had from the days of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, infected <hi>France</hi> in ſundry places; and the Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots being ſtronger and more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then formerly, began to think of revenging the cruelties that had been exerciſed towards them; and their deſire was to commence with the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> as well for the intereſt of their Religion (to which the <hi>Guiſes</hi> were profeſſed Enemies) as for the benefit of the State, of which, out of animoſity they had already pronounced them Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57675:38"/>they wanted only a head as valiant as the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and it is poſſible he would have accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, if the conſpiracy <hi>d'Amboiſe</hi> had ſucceeded. To juſtifie their deſigns, Libels were ſpred abroad, and it was ſaid the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> (who had a great deal of wit) was Author of them himſelf. They Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated that by the Laws of that Kingdom, neither Women nor Strangers were to be admitted to the cheif Miniſtery, and many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples they cited to ſhow, that the Adminiſtration of Cardinals was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fatal to <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Libels were highly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> and above all, to the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine;</hi> either becauſe his Miniſtery juſtified the examples which were alleaged, or becauſe his Enemies Reaſons were ſtrong enough to juſtifie the truth of what they publiſhed. He ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Counſellor of the Parliament of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57675:39"/>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> called <hi>du Burg</hi> (a perſon of ſingular merit and vertue:) This <hi>du Burg</hi> had been a priſoner a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat twelve moneth, only for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing himſelf a <hi>Lutheran</hi> (for in thoſe days nothing was more crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) and if all thoſe who died for Religion, had taken the right ſide, the antient <hi>Romans</hi> would have had fewer Martyrs, then the Reigns of <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Nineth. Leaſt <hi>de Burg</hi> ſhould make worſer diſcoveries, then thoſe which they imputed to him wrongfully al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, order was given to his Judges (who in reſpect of his great parts, were inclined to give him longer time to confeſs) to condemn him with as much ſpeed as could conſiſt with the glory of God, which was exactly performed to the great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine.</hi> The poor Gentleman took his death with extraordinary conſtancy; his countenance was quiet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57675:39"/>he exhorted ſuch of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, as were preſent at his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, to lay down their lives as freely (if there were occaſion) as he; aſſuring them, that Death was the happieſt thing in the World, when Men ſuffered in ſo excellent a Cauſe. His words made a deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the hearts of thoſe who had already imbibed that new opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and they believed their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion infinitely the better, becauſe a perſon of his wiſdom and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacity, had choſe to die rather then to entertain any other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Burgs</hi> death begot great ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity in that Kingdom: The Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots firſt deſign was to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged it by force; but the fear they had of being too weak, made them take new meaſures, and change their reſolution: Some would have it, that they intended no farther then the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> others were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, their deſign would have gone
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57675:40"/>farther, if it had ſucceeded. Be it how it will, their conſpiracy which makes ſo much noiſe in our Hiſtory, and paſſes under the name of the Conſpiracy <hi>d'Ambois,</hi> was diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Renaudie,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigord</hi> (a great <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er incendiary) imparted it to an Advocate of his acquaintance; the Advocate to a Maſter of Requeſts, called <hi>Vouze;</hi> and <hi>Vouze</hi> (either ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring the deſign, or deſirous to do a piece of ſervice that might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be recompenſed) diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the <hi>Guiſes.</hi> Nothing was ever more horrid then the paſſages at <hi>Ambois</hi> for a whole week toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: The blood ran down the Streets, and the Throats were cut of all ſuch as were ſuſpected to have conſpired.</p>
               <p>Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> who had as much influence upon the King as ſhe could wiſh, and retained ſtill an implacable enmity to the Prince of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57675:40"/>
                  <hi>Condé,</hi> thought this a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deſtroy him: She pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed pardon to two of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, if they would accuſe him of being the principal Agent: They accuſed him, and, with him, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral and <hi>Dandelot:</hi> It is true, one part of their impeachment was right, and if that enterpriſe had ſucceeded, the Prince, Admiral, and <hi>Dandelot</hi> would have declared; but the poor people that accuſed him, knew nothing of that, and the King knowing as little of Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles deſign, ſeemed notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be of her Plot, for he promiſed them pardon (as ſhe had ingaged) if they charged him effectually. But this promiſe gave her no little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet; ſhe was afraid when theſe falſe witneſſes were at liberty, that they would recant: She thought fit to conſult her Father, the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> in the Caſe; told him what her hatred to the Prince had
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57675:41"/>prompted her to do, and withal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with her apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Mareſchal hated the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and his Daughter was too far engaged to retire; the Prince muſt be ruined, or ſhe was undone: Though the King did her the honor to love her, and had promiſed her protection; yet it would have coſt him no little trouble to have juſtified a crime of ſo important a nature. To leave theſe poor Creatures no poſſibility of betraying her, certain perſons were ſent to the priſon, to which the Witneſſes were carried back, who having taken them aſide, ſlew them immediately, and they deſerved it for their treachery.</p>
               <p>The rupture of this marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Prince <hi>de Joinville,</hi> and Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> interrupt the amity betwixt the <hi>Guiſes</hi> and the Mareſchal; for they continued the beſt Friends in the World. In the mean time, the <hi>Guiſes</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57675:41"/>gave orders for the arreſting the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> next morning; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding with all poſſible vigor, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſumption, that he was really guilty, from the teſtimony of the two falſe witneſſes which they had carefully examined, and were not a little joyed to find their evidence ſo clear: For as to the ſecret which Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to her Father, it was too tender and delicate to be intruſted to any body beſides.</p>
               <p>During all this confuſion, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral was at his houſe at <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> where with impatience he expected the ſucceſs of the conſpiracy; and <hi>Dandelot</hi> coming to <hi>Ambois</hi> (where the Court was at that time) having met, upon the Road, with ſome of the Conſpirators who were eſcaped, fled into <hi>Brittany,</hi> where his Lady had a very ſtrong Caſtle. There was none of them at Court but the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> who continued
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57675:42"/>there to ſupport the enterpriſe as occaſion was offered; in ſo much, as none was in ſuch manifeſt danger as he; for he had undoubtedly loſt his head, if he had been arreſted: But about two of the clock in the morning, before the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> orders were to be put in execution, one of his Valets <hi>de Chamber,</hi> ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly awaked him, and delivered him a Note, which he had juſt then received, with commands to deliver it immediately without conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether he was awake or a ſleep, for the Prince had never an affair that concerned him more near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> opened it, and found it from a Woman, but he could not imagine the hand; however, that which was in it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to looſe no time in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining from whence it came. It contained only theſe few words,</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57675:42"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>Save your ſelf Sir, or your are a dead Man; I have no time to inform you any farther.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Prince was too ſenſible of his guilt, to deliberate what he had to do. He got up, and departed out of the Town with all poſſible diligence. The Guards at the Gates having yet no notice of what was reſolved, were ſo far from obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his paſſage, that they ſuffered him to paſs with all the reſpect that was due to his quality. He retired to <hi>Orleans,</hi> where his reputation was great, his friends conſiderable, and ready to ſacrifice themſelves for his intereſt: He had not been long gone, before the Kings Guards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted his Lodgings, and were not a little troubled to find him eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: His accuſers were ſent for, but both of them were murdered, and no account could be given by whoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57675:43"/>orders: The ſuſpition was ſtronger againſt the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> then againſt Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> and yet it was the Mareſchal, not the Prince, who had cauſed them to be ſlain. Generally people are moſt jealous of the perſon accuſed, and the Court was of opinion, that the Prince inraged to ſee himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, had revenged himſelf upon his accuſers before he had fled. By the Kings order, Proceſs was framed againſt him, which if he had been taken, would have certainly been finiſhed; but finding him eſcaped, it was judged imprudent to carry things to extremity, and they rather choſe to pretend ignorance of that conſpiracy, then to give occaſion for new.</p>
               <p>This temper and moderation in their Politicks, did not at all accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate with the fury of Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> ſhe complained of it to the King, who acquainted her
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57675:43"/>with the Reaſons, upon which the Council had proceeded in that manner; and told her, That the ruine of the Prince was but defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for he would never pardon him, or forget his inſolence to her: Some few days after, the Court re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from <hi>Ambois</hi> to <hi>Orleans,</hi> where the States General were to meet. The Prince was departed from thence to the Admiral at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillon,</hi> and from thence to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> who was at that time in his Government in <hi>Guyenne.</hi> Paſſing by <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> he ſhewed the Admiral the Note by which his life was preſerved; the Admiral knew the hand, and aſſured him it came from the Mareſchal <hi>de S. Andres</hi> Lady; but the Prince found ſo little probability in that, that he could not poſſibly believe it.</p>
               <p>In the interim, the time approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Convention of the Eſtates.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57675:44"/>All the Princes of the Blood, and all the great Officers of the Crown, were required to be preſent, upon pain of being degraded from their Dignities, and reputed acceſſories in the Conſpiracy. The Admiral not believing himſelf accuſed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at the place, but the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> (being leſs conſiderable at Court then the <hi>Guiſes</hi>) refuſed to be preſent; and the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> (who had been practiſing in all the Towns thorow which he paſſed) was ſo far from obeying the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that he raiſed Men with the Moneys he received from the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> to remove the <hi>Guiſes</hi> by force of Arms, which was concluded to be the only way, conſidering the difficulty of a Conjuration, where ſo many were to be intruſted; that it was hard but ſome of them would either be treacherous or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent. The Careſſes wherewith the Admiral was treated at <hi>Orleans,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:57675:44"/>did eaſily perſwade him, that he was not at all ſuſpected, and that the Note ſent to the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> was but an artifice of the Mareſchal and the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> to remove him from Court, and render him ſuſpect. He writ to the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and conjured them not to make themſelves crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: He aſſured them, they would be gratiouſly received, and that their preſence was neceſſary to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and correct the power of the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> which was like to be too potent, unleſs reſtrained by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Princes of the Blood. Theſe Letters not prevailing, he writ again, and ſent them word, That it was by the Queens orders, who was grown weary (as well as the reſt of the State) of the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Tyranny of the <hi>Guiſes;</hi> and leaſt they ſhould queſtion the truth of his Letters, he ſent them another, in which the Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57675:45"/>explained her ſelf, under her own hand, and conjured them to reſcue her from the oppreſſions of that family.</p>
               <p>This Letter was effectual, and brought them to the Lure: The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire which they had to wreſt the Government out of the hands of the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> made them forget that the Queen was the moſt diſſembling Princeſs of her time. The King of <hi>Navarre</hi> would needs go, and (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his repugnancy) preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, that he was not able to deny him.</p>
               <p>Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> (who had ſworn never to pardon the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> for the diſhonor which he had occaſioned to her, and his inſolent expreſſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon) choſe that moment wherein his Majeſty was in his extaſie of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to beſeech him (if he loved her as he pretended) to revenge and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57675:45"/>rid her of a perſon, whoſe very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was a ſecret reproach to her, which ſhe was not able to bear. What can a Man refuſe his Miſtreſs at ſuch a time? or rather, what will he not grant? The King need not have been in love, to have been blind; he was of an age incapable of reflections; he promiſed her the Prince ſhould die; and would have promiſed her more, if ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it. As ſoon as the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> came to <hi>Orleans,</hi> he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his Guards; but the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was arreſted and put into cuſtody: They revived his Proceſs that had been laid aſide; accuſed him to have had a principal hand in the conſpiracy <hi>d'Ambois,</hi> and to have cauſed his accuſers to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, to conceal the evidence of his crime: The King and Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle inſtructed his Judges; after which it was a hard matter to prove himſelf innocent. As often as they
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57675:46"/>charged him with the murder of the Witneſſes, he appeared ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſturbed, and that diſturbance was taken by thoſe who were to judge him as a great argument of his guilt. They confronted him with one <hi>Sague,</hi> Secretary to the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> whom either the fear of the Rack, or the hopes of a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence had made to tell dangerous things. He was amazed to ſee that unhappy perſon (who had received great obligations from him) to hold intelligence with his Enemies, and endeavor his deſtruction; and this ſurpriſe was ſeconded by another far more incomprehenſible. One of his Guards, and a Man who would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing for Money, gave him privately a Note that he had received from an unknown perſon, who had conjured him to deliver it into the Princes own hand: The Prince opened it, and found pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently by the character, that it came
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57675:46"/>from the ſame perſon who had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him ſo ſeaſonably to preſerve himſelf at <hi>Ambois:</hi> He doubted not but now alſo ſhe had ſomething of great importance to advertiſe, and in that opinion he read it haſtily, and found theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <l>TAke my advice Sir, and prepare for your</l>
                     <l>death; it is to no purpoſe to think of a</l>
                     <l>defence: The perſon that proſecutes you, is</l>
                     <l>a Friend to the State; nothing appears</l>
                     <l>more guilty then you: They who</l>
                     <l>(out of true Zeal and Loyalty to the King)</l>
                     <l>have rendered you ſo Criminal, were</l>
                     <l>honeſt Men, and incapable to be</l>
                     <l>ſuborned. I have too great an intereſt</l>
                     <l>in the miſcheifs that you have done</l>
                     <l>in your life, to conceal from you</l>
                     <l>that the decree of your death is no longer</l>
                     <l>ſo great a ſecret. Thoſe wicked fellows</l>
                     <l>(for ſo it is, you are pleaſed to call them)</l>
                     <l>who have adventured to accuſe you, deſerve</l>
                     <l>a recompence as juſtly, as you do</l>
                     <l>that death which is preparing for you; it is only</l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:57675:47"/>
                     <l>your Vanity perſwades you, that</l>
                     <l>your Merit has created you Enemies,</l>
                     <l>and that it is not your Crimes,</l>
                     <l>which have cauſed your diſgrace: Deny</l>
                     <l>with your uſual impudence and obſtinacy,</l>
                     <l>that you ever had any hand in the</l>
                     <l>wicked and deteſtable practices of the</l>
                     <l>Conſpiracy of <hi>Ambois:</hi>It is not</l>
                     <l>(whatever you imagine to the contrary) im-</l>
                     <l>Poſſible to convict you. Fare</l>
                     <l>as you pleaſe, but prepare your ſelf</l>
                     <l>well.</l>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The poor Prince perceiving eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body to inſult upon his miſery, had like to have loſt all patience: He could not comprehend upon what reaſon the ſame perſon, who had advertiſed him ſo kindly before, to preſerve himſelf, ſhould trample upon him now unneceſſarily in ſo ſad a conjuncture. Either he thought he had never merited from her the leaſt concern for his life, or elſe he
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57675:47"/>believed he had deſerved what ſhe had done for him; and though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he had not actually expreſſed himſelf in her ſervice ſo far, as to oblige her to that favor; yet he had never done any thing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe her, or provoke her to that inſolence. However this way of proceeding was ſo different from her former, that he took the Letter (which he had thrown upon the Table) read it over again, and could not find one word in it, but of injury and reproach. He folded it, and unfolded it ſeveral times to ſee if there was no myſtery; for ſtanding as he did, accuſed of High Treaſon, it was dangerous to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their advice too plainly, how favorably ſoever they might ſtand. He ſearched and examined ſo long, that at length he found what he looked for. This Letter to read it, as Letters are generally read, was without queſtion, highly diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57675:48"/>but to read it but half, that is after you have read the firſt line, to skip the ſecond, then the fourth, then the ſixth, and ſo on with the reſt, it will be found in theſe terms.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <l>TAke my advice Sir, and prepare for your</l>
                     <l>defence; the perſon that proſecutes you, is</l>
                     <l>more guilty then you. They who</l>
                     <l>have rendered you ſo criminal, were</l>
                     <l>ſuborned: I have too great an intereſt</l>
                     <l>in your life, to conceal from you</l>
                     <l>ſo great aſecret. Thoſe wicked fellows</l>
                     <l>who have adventured to accuſe you, deſerve</l>
                     <l>that death which is preparing for you. It is only</l>
                     <l>your Merit has created you Enemies</l>
                     <l>which have cauſed your diſgrace: Deny</l>
                     <l>that you ever had any hand in the</l>
                     <l>Conſpiracy of <hi>Ambois:</hi> It is not</l>
                     <l>poſſible to convict you. Fare</l>
                     <l>well.</l>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>There was great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two Letters: The Prince owned himſelf infinitely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57675:48"/>to the perſon who had writ it, for the ſhare which ſhe took in his misfortunes, and the hints that ſhe gave him; and he was extreamly taken with her invention, to ſignifie her kindneſs ſo neatly, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing her ſelf (for certainly had the Letter miſcarried, and been brought to the King, it would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have advanced her, then crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her any trouble.) Very impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent he was to know this Lady, to whom he was ſo prodigiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, that he might at leaſt make her ſee how ſenſible he was of her favors: He could not make himſelf believe it was Madam la Mareſchal, as the Admiral had aſſured him; and the hatred that for a long time had been betwixt their two Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, was indeed ſufficient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him.</p>
               <p>Whileſt he was pondering with himſelf, and beating his brains to find out the Author of this Letter.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57675:49"/>His Judges came into his Chamber to interrogate him the laſt time; he denied very conſtantly, that he had any part in the conſpiracy of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bois;</hi> maintained that his accuſers had been ſuborned, and then mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by his Enemies, leaſt they ſhould have recanted, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered in their teſtimony; but not one word of the Letter which he had received: And though he had been ſure to have cleared himſelf by ſhowing it in its natural ſenſe, he would rather have choſen to die, then have been ungrateful to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who had endeavored to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him with ſo much generoſity. The Judges (whoſe integrity was not to be byaſſed by favor) could find nothing of clear evidence againſt the Prince; but thoſe who were delegated by the King, and Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to be ſure to find him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (as if whatever they did for their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57675:49"/>own preferment would be juſt) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that they had farther proof, and the number of them being greater then the other; they framed an Arreſt againſt him (which the Chancellor <hi>de l'Hoſpital</hi> refuſed very wiſely to ſign) and ordered him to be beheaded at the ſame hour when the States entered into their Houſe. But the King, Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André,</hi> nor the Judges, who had been very buſie in procuring this Arreſt, had not the pleaſure to ſee it executed. The King fell ill, in the mean time, upon which, the Queen-Mother cauſed execution to be ſuſpended; not ſo much in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Prince, as of her own particular intereſt. She had the ſole Regency of the State, and doubted not, but if the King died, the face of affairs would alter, her other Children being in their mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; which minority, being a great favorer of ambition, ſhe feared that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57675:50"/>if the grandeur of the <hi>Guiſes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained without counterpoiſe, it would become as dangerous as the practices of the Princes of the Blood.</p>
               <p>This providence of the Queen-Mother was not impertinent. The King died, and the authority of Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> died with him. To avoid the reſentments of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and thoſe of the Queen-Mother (who hated her mortally, for that ſhe had wrought her ſelf ſo cunningly into the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the King) Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André</hi> retired into a Nunnery at <hi>Long Champ. Francis</hi> the Second having no Children by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the next of his Brothers, who was Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him by the name of <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth.</p>
               <p>To diſſipate the troubles which hindered Queen <hi>Catherine</hi> from the peaceable injoyment of her Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57675:50"/>ſhe endeavored an accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation betwixt the Princes of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Lorraine.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party declined it, and the Treaties being well received both on the one ſide, and the other, all was compoſed, and the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> diſcharged of his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by an eminent Arreſt of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>I am telling a very true ſtory, and yet it is almoſt incredible: The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was ſo naturally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, that he fell in love even at the time that Sentence of Death was pronounced againſt him: I am of opinion, there is not an example of any Man that choſe ſo improper a ſeaſon as then: Whileſt he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain what would be the event of the Kings ſickneſs, he reflected ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the Letter which he had received, and found it ſo full of kindneſs, that it would have been a ſecond death to him, to have died
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57675:51"/>ingrateful. The deſire which he had to know to whom he was ſo highly obliged; the deſire he had to teſtifie his acknowledgments; and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he took in his Obligation, were things which I call love, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they were ſo.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Parliament had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the honor of this Prince, his love thought it time to act for his intereſt. The Prince concealing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the Admiral, ſhewed him the Letter which was ſent him in priſon. The Admiral aſſured him again, that it was from Madam la Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> and that he knew the hand perfectly well. <hi>If it be ſo</hi> (ſaid the Prince) <hi>I love Madam la Mareſchal</hi> de S. André; <hi>and all that you can ſay to divert me, ſhall not hinder me from loving her eternally. The hatred which was betwixt me and her Husband (and perhaps is ſtill) is increaſed thereby: For the accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation made by the Queen, is in truth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57675:51"/>but a palliated Peace; and beſides, if my Reaſons of State were not, my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Love are abundantly ſufficient to make me hate him; if for nothing but being Husband to a Lady, for whom I have ſo great an affection. But to return to Madam</hi> la Mareſchalle, <hi>ſince the animoſity</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>betwixt her Husband and me, hindered her not from making ſo generous efforts to oblige me: I muſt love her, and that love without queſtion will laſt: It is founded on gratitude, which is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to which I ſhall pretend as long as I live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> was not own Mother to Madamoiſelle <hi>de S. André.</hi> The Mareſchal had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her Son three years ſince, and ſhe was, at the moſt, but two and twenty years of age, if ſhe was ſo much. She was not altogether ſo beautiful as her Daughter in Law, but ſhe had beauty enough to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate any Man; and as nice as the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57675:52"/>Prince was, had wherewithal to make her ſelf beloved by him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aſſiſtance of the favors which ſhe had done him. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> was grown white, and the fatigues of the War, how great ſoever they had been, had contributed leſs to it, then five and fifty years, which he confeſſed (though his greyneſs ſpoke him at leaſt ſixty;) but an old man marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a young Lady makes always the beſt of his age, and will be ſure to conceal ſomething. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was very young, as hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a perſon as belonged to the Court, and was beſides of excellent parts. Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> was not ignorant of it; for ſhe alſo had her ſhare, and upon the bare repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Prince, had conceived ſo great an eſteem for him, as gave her a concern for every thing that befel him. Her Husband (to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her for that, of which his age
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57675:52"/>had deprived her) had a ſtrange kindneſs for her, which would have been altogether unuſeful, had not ſhe taken advantage of it to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Prince; he impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her all the tranſactions of State. It was from him, that ſhe had underſtood, that the Prince was to be arreſted, when ſhe gave him ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at two a clock in the Morning to eſcape from <hi>Ambois.</hi> It was he again, that was ſo weak to truſt her with a ſecret, which his Daughter would not have committed to any body but him; and certainly it had been ſufficient to ruine them both, had Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> been as imprudent as her Husband.</p>
               <p>The Prince was much diſquieted with his new paſſion, and more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous for his Miſtreſs, then his life, though he knew not who ſhe was, (for whatever the Admiral could ſay to aſſure him, he ſtill doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57675:53"/>whom he was ſo ſtrictly obliged.) The Prince made a viſit to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> and expreſſed great ſatisfaction in the accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the Queen-Mother had made; but Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> being abroad, the Prince was ſo troubled that the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> perceiving it in his looks, imagined that he paid him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement with regret, and that he was ſtill his Enemy at the heart. His viſit was but ſhort, however he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed it to the Mareſchal as well as he could. he told him, that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions were, for the future, to live in perfect amity with him, and to viſit him as oft as he had opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> had been to wait upon the Queen, and came in juſt as the Prince was taking his leave of her Husband; ſo unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a ſight of him, put her to the bluſh. And the Prince, though
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57675:53"/>not altogether ſo ſubject to bluſh, perceived ſomething in himſelf, that he was not accuſtomed to feel, which privately ſuggeſted, that this was the Lady to whom he was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely obliged: He made her a ſhort complement, but ſo perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and myſterious, that her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band could make nothing of it, though ſhe underſtood it perfectly, and was the more pleaſed with it, becauſe it was not intelligible to all the World. She anſwered too in ſuch a manner, as gave no jealouſie to the Mareſchal, and yet the Prince thought ſomethings of it very kind; not that it was effectually ſo, but he deſired it ſhould have been ſo, and men do eaſily believe what they do paſſionately deſire. They part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Prince, and Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle</hi> infinitely well pleaſed at their enterview, and the Mareſchal himſelf at the ſame rate, neither
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57675:54"/>better nor worſe, then before the viſit was made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100-151" type="pages">
               <p>At night they met again at Court: Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> was come thither to pay her devoir, and the Prince was come thither to ſee her. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay to the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> took him aſide, to the great ſatisfaction of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> who was ambitious of nothing more then an opportunity of entertaining the Lady, which he had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to attempt whileſt her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was preſent. Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle,</hi> who caſt her eyes every moment upon the Prince, and was ſtill encountred with the ſame glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from him; thought ſhe ſhould not offend him, if ſhe gave him a ſmall opportunity to accoſt her; and that he might do it with more eaſe, and ſhe have occaſion to quit the Ladies, with whom ſhe was in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57675:54"/>ſome impertinent diſcourſe, ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended her Watch was down, and went to ſee what a clock it was at a little clock in the Queens Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber: This project ſucceeded as ſhe deſired. The Prince accoſted her, and finding there was no body could hear him but herſelf. <hi>I do not know Madam</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>whether this be the hour that you would have it: For my own part, I never expect to find one ſo favorable as to give me opportunity to teſtifie the Sentiments I have of your incomparable goodneſs; for ſince I am at liberty, I ought to be aſhamed to have made no better uſe of a bleſſing that I have received whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> replied to the Princes civility, with as much modeſty on her ſide, pretending ſhe underſtood nothing of what he ſaid. He explained himſelf; ſhe had really an eſteem for him, and perhaps what ſhe thought nothing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57675:55"/>but eſteem, was indeed ſomething more then ſhe imagined: However ſhe owned it not poſitively, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to run a risk in a thing that might reflect upon her reputation, before ſhe underſtood him better then at that time ſhe did. <hi>Why Madam,</hi> ſaid the Prince, <hi>is it poſſible I ſhould be ſo unhappy, as to ow my life to any but your ſelf? I believe</hi> (ſaid Madam <hi>la Mareſchal) it is to your own innocence you ow it, and to no body elſe; and (ſuppoſing that was not ſufficient to abſolve you) a priſoner of your birth, and accomliſhments, hath greater priviledges then ordinary. Theſe are my thoughts, but if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire I ſhould rather come over to yours, and believe it to ſome other perſon that you are obliged for your life, though it were to your greateſt enemy, I do not ſee how you could call it an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. It is one Madam</hi> (replied the Prince) <hi>and ſo much the greater, becauſe I propoſed no happineſs equal
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57675:55"/>to my being obliged to you: It would have perſwaded me, I had not been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together indifferent to you, and the duty which I had ought you, would have juſtified a paſſion that I find in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in me, and cannot but take this opportunity to diſcover: You would, I ſay, have added love to my gratitude ...... I ſee Madam</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the Prince, ſomething more haſtily then before) <hi>that word to which you are not accuſtomed, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to a vertue ſo tender, and ſo delicate as yours; but my error is the cauſe of my boldneſs. I thought I could not have acquitted my ſelf of the duty which I ought you, but by loving you intirely: And the more love I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the more grateful I thought my ſelf: However Madam, I am moſt deſperately in love; the Letters which I received, contributed to make me ſo; and from the time I fancied them from your Ladiſhip, I have ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed my ſelf to love you, that if at
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:57675:56"/>preſent, it offends you, you ought to excuſe it as proceeding from a habit that is not eaſily removed.</hi> Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> had the good word of every body, and had hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved her reputation againſt the attacks of Envy it ſelf, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her one of the moſt celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſons of her time; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe could not but lend an ear to the paſſion of ſo great a man as the Prince of <hi>Condé.</hi> She hearkned to all that the ardor of his affection could dictate to his tongue; and when he had done, retired without giving him any anſwer, rather to irritate and foment, then to revenge or extirpate the love which he had conceived. Since her daughter in law was recluſe in the Nunnery at <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champ,</hi> no body at Court was able to contend with her; ſo as ſhe had many Servants, and among the reſt <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,</hi> and own Brother to the Prince
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57675:56"/>of <hi>Condé:</hi> But being reſolved, if ſhe entertained any, to have a lover whoſe excellent accompliſhments, might in ſome meaſure excuſe her weakneſſes, if it ſhould be thought ſo; and that King being timorous and irreſolute, ſhe continued firm in her inclinations to the Prince.</p>
               <p>Two Rivals are never long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out emulation, and how ſtrong ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ligaments of blood may be, love will eaſily break them when they become obſtacles to their deſigns. The King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> who before was an Enemy to the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> joyning with their party, rendered it more ſtrong; for ſome few days before, by the Edict of Pacification, he was declared Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General of the Kingdom. The War being not quite extinct, it was no hard matter to revive it, and <hi>Fortune</hi> preſented them with a pretence which both parties did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually deſire.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:57675:57"/>
               <p>The firſt of <hi>March,</hi> in the year One thouſand five hundred ſixty and two, as the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was paſſing by the little Town of <hi>Vaſſi,</hi> ſome of his retinue, in curioſity, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into a Houſe where the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes</hi> were at their devotion, and perhaps treated them with deriſion; which being diſguſted by the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes,</hi> a quarrel began, and from words they came inſenſibly to blows: The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> running in amongſt them, to prevent any diſorder, his preſence revived the hatred which the <hi>Hugonotes</hi> had for him; and one of them had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to throw a ſtone at him, and broke his head; which ſo animated his people againſt them, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he was not able to reſtrain them: And though he uſed the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his authority to hinder them, above fifty of the <hi>Hugonotes</hi> were ſlain, and more then two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred wounded. This was the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:57675:57"/>at <hi>Vaſſi,</hi> which hath made ſuch a noiſe in our Hiſtory, and was a <hi>praeludium</hi> to all the Wars which ſucceeded, not only in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Nineth, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth.</p>
               <p>Report (that never preſents any thing fairly, and as it is) carried the news of this outrage to the Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> and accompanied it with ſo many ill circumſtances, as gave him occaſion to preſume, that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was the Author. He departed immediately to attend the King at <hi>Monceaux,</hi> where, for ſome days, he was diverting himſelf with the Queen-Mother, and his Brothers, the Dukes of <hi>Anjon</hi> and <hi>Alencon,</hi> in whoſe preſence he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to his Majeſty of the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had uſed (contrary to the Articles of the Treaty) to the prejudice of the Priviledges granted to that new
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57675:58"/>opinion; but by the coldneſs of his anſwer, he found he was not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect reparation, unleſs it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded with his Sword in his hand. He diſpatched Meſſengers privately to the cheif of his party, who ſince the late pacification were diſperſed into ſeveral Provinces; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them a Rendezvous at <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> where (in ſpight of the Arreſt that was given againſt him, in the time of the late King) his name was highly conſiderable. He was much pleaſed with ſo fair a pretence of renewing the War; for his valor could not be idle: But this Martial inclination was much impugned by another, which at that time, was more ſtrong upon his heart; and the Paſſion which he had for the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André,</hi> was incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with a deſign that would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him ſo far from her. The Queen Mother, who for her own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, apprehended they would
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57675:58"/>ſeiſe upon the King, in whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all her authority was placed, conveyed him with all diligence to <hi>Paris;</hi> but becauſe the Cabal of the <hi>Guiſes</hi> (which ſhe feared no leſs then that of the Prince) were as power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſhe thought him not ſafe there, but two days after removed him to <hi>Fountainbleau.</hi> The King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> whoſe character of Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Kingdom, obliged him to remain ſome time at <hi>Paris,</hi> to give out ſuch orders as were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the good of the State, fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not every day to multiply his viſits to Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André,</hi> who did not reckon it among her good fortunes to receive them; her heart being too full of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> to afford room for any body elſe. To increaſe the good opinion of her Husband, and give him farther aſſurance of her fidelity, which he thought already incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible (and yet it was tottering at
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57675:59"/>that very time) ſhe diſcovered to him the deſigns of the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,</hi> who the day before had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated his affection; and told him, that after ſo mortal an injury, the very ſight of him would be a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, from which ſhe would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be excuſed.</p>
               <p>the Mareſchal raviſhed with the vertue of his Wife, granted her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and conſented, that the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> ſhould be requeſted to diſcontinue his viſits: For his own part, though the offence which the King had committed, was of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable nature, yet the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal ſuſpended his reſentment, leaſt it ſhould ſeparate him from his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ingage him with the Prince. The next day the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> renewing his viſits to Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle,</hi> was told ſhe was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: He asked for the Mareſchal, and was anſwered, That he alſo was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. <hi>This is not true</hi> (replied the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57675:59"/>King of <hi>Navarre) the Prince of</hi> Condé <hi>is here, I ſee by his Liveries, and Madam</hi> la Mareſchelle <hi>is with him, for it is not to her Husband he makes his viſits:</hi> And having ſaid ſo, he preſumed ſo far upon the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of his quality, as to go up the Stairs into the Ladies appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where he found the Prince, as he ſaid. It is moſt certain, the ſight of a Rival, who is ſuſpected to be in greater favor, diſturbs a man exceedingly where his Paſſion is ſtrong. The King of <hi>Navarre</hi> could not ſupport the affront which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>la Mareſchelle</hi> had done him, in preferring his Brother, whom he looked upon as much inferior to himſelf, in reſpect of the inequality of his power; but the Mareſchals Lady regarded not that: On the contrary, the Princes extraordinary merit, made her look upon other things as the injuſtice of <hi>Fortune,</hi> to which, if it had been in her
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57675:60"/>power to have adminiſtred a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, there is nothing but ſhe would have enterpriſed, to have proved her ſelf the leſs blind of the two. <hi>You have reaſon Madam</hi> (ſaid the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> as he came in) <hi>to deny your ſelf to be at home; it is not grateful to be interrupted in ſo pleaſant a privacy: I ſee I have taken an ill time to viſit you, which perhaps you will not eaſily pardon.</hi> The Lady was much diſturbed at the ſight of the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to have been ſurpriſed with the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing paſſed betwixt them, that <hi>Fame</hi> it ſelf could reproach; and aſſuming an air more fierce then uſual, ſhe replied, <hi>That in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy ſhe injoyed with his Brother, ſhe feared no ſuch affront as ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not many days before; and that to prevent a ſecond from the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhe would take her meaſures ſo, as he ſhould never find her alone. I ſuppoſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57675:60"/>I underſtand you Madam,</hi> replied the King of <hi>Navarre, you have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that I ſhould find you alone, but you are not offended to be alone with another; and the orders you left with your Porter, aſſures me, that I ſhould have done you a kindneſs to have left you ſo now. Since you are pleaſed Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur,</hi> replied the Lady. (For though he was King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> being born a Subject to the King of <hi>France,</hi> they called him not <hi>SIRE,</hi> but only Monſeigneur, as firſt Prince of the Blood; but Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> being in a Paſſion againſt him, thought her ſelf excuſable in that point, and not obliged to thoſe punctilioes with a Prince who had treated her in that manner.) <hi>Since you are pleaſed Monſieur</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>to name your ſelf, as if you had feared I ſhould have imputed the affront, which you have done me, to ſome other perſon, I will not rob you of the honor of ſo noble an action: For a need I
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57675:61"/>ſhall go farther, and confeſs to you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly, that the orders given to my Porter, were intended only for you. This is too much Madam,</hi> replied the King of <hi>Navarre, and the preſence of that perſon whom you prefer, exacted not from you ſo blind a complaiſance. I have declared I love you, and am ready to do it again; if it be a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it is a weakneſs that may without diſhonor be owned: I know not (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) upon what reaſon you condemn it in me, and approve it in another.</hi> Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> would have returned him an anſwer, but the Prince prevented it, and told the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> in ſome kind of heat, <hi>That he conſidered neither his Seniority, nor Majeſty, when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Madam</hi> la Mareſchalle <hi>was at ſtake; that he forgot there, what perhaps he might ow him in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place; that what ſhe condemned in him, was condemnable in all the World; and that he ought to judge
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57675:61"/>more favorably of her vertue, ſeeing the temptation of his Crown was not able to ſtagger it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſpeak Sir, a little too high</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the King of <hi>Navarre) but I do not admire it. Madam</hi> la Mareſchalle <hi>inſpires courage where ſhe pleaſes; yet ſhe muſt give me leave to queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo bold a defender of her reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contributes much to its eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and for what you would have me judge of her vertue, the great care you take of it, is a great means to keep me from a raſh and temerarious conſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adieu Madam,</hi> ſaid he, addreſſing himſelf towards her, <hi>I do not envy my Brother the favors which you ſhow him: It is but reaſon he ſhould be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored in his love, who has had ſo little of it in his fortune; and if your Ladiſhip will give me leave to be free, I must tell you, I perceive that to be younger ſeven or eight years, is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that makes a man much more
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57675:62"/>conſiderable to you.</hi> And having ſaid ſo, he went out reſolved to revenge himſelf, both upon the Lady and Prince. Though there was nothing in the paſſion which the Prince had for Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> at which, the moſt nice and ſcrupulous Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue could have been ſcandalized, yet he was not a little diſcompoſed, that the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> ſhould find them together. He made large Apologies that his viſit was ſo unſeaſonable, and promiſed to ſhow his reſentment ſo far, (if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſhould any ways intrench up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her honor) that the Lady was not only affected, but forbore not to teſtifie it.</p>
               <p>He had not had the happineſs to diſcourſe with her, ſince their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the Queens Lodgings; and notwithſtanding all the pains which he took to create an occaſion, ſhe kept her ſelf carefully upon her guard, and indeed declined him as
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:57675:62"/>much as ſhe could, leaſt the eſteem ſhe had for him ſhould be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an intelligence with his affection for her. The Prince in this anxiety being about to leave <hi>Paris,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the uncertainty of the Wars, could not reſolve to leave the Town without explaining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf once more to Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe;</hi> and to prevent her avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, he made her a viſit at her own Houſe, where he had been a compleat hour before the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> interrupted them. Whileſt he was alone with her, he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelf ſo tenderly, and with ſo much teſtimony of his love, repreſented to her the poſſibility that this might be the laſt moment in which he might ever ſee her again; that the fortune of the Wars was uncertain; and, that if ſhe ſuffered him to depart without ſatisfying him, that it was to her he ought all his obligations, his life
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57675:63"/>would be a burden to him, of which he would endeavor to eaſe himſelf, the firſt Battle he ſhould be ingaged in. He, I ſay, expreſſed himſelf ſo paſſionately in theſe terms, that at length ſhe could not hold, but cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. <hi>Live Sir, live; and if you have any paſſion for me, make good uſe of that ſervice which I have endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to render you. Alas Madam,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Prince, <hi>how unprofitable is all your kindneſs, if your Vertue will not permit my acknowledgments to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the degree of esteem! As many times as I have preſumed to declare my affections, ſo many times have your eyes (which I always carefully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) checked and reprehended my boldneſs; and now even at this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I ſee your colour change, and your modeſty, as it were, upbraiding me, for ſetting ſo great a value upon your generoſity and goodneſs. It is true Madam, when at firſt you complained to me of the importunity of the King
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57675:63"/>of</hi> Navarre, <hi>I thought myſelf ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, that I could not do the ſame thing, without giving your Ladiſhip the ſame offence: But when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that he had never been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived but with indifferency, and could not pretend to any obligation upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your favors, I looked upon the Declaration which he had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to make, as an intrenchment upon your honor; whereas you having been ſo noble as to concern your ſelf for me, even to the ſaving of my life, I thought my ſelf obliged to love you upon much better grounds then he; and to ſpeak truth, I thought I could not conceal it without the higheſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was their diſcourſe before the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> came in; and the Prince had negotiated ſo well, that he had prevailed with her to permit his affection. <hi>But, I beſeech you,</hi> (ſaid Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> to the Prince) <hi>never ſee me again after
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57675:64"/>the conſent which you have extorted from me: I conſent upon no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but that for the future your preſence does not reproach my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and it is by your obedience in this point, that I must be convinced of your love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words went very near him, yet as ſoon as the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> was gone, he took his leave alſo. This parting was not however without great trouble; it coſt the Prince many a ſigh, and Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> who had forced her ſelf much to conceal her own ſorrow, ceaſed to conſtrain her ſelf as ſoon as he was out of ſight, and paid him in tears for all the ſighs he had laid out.</p>
               <p>Things being in this poſture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Prince and Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle,</hi> the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> more in ſpight to his Brother, then any religious conſideration, turned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and went over to the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57675:64"/>Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Before this, the Conneſtable <hi>de Montmorency</hi> had always been of the Princes party, but being informed that the Prince had moved in Counſel for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of ſome gifts, and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf the mark at which he principally aimed, becauſe in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, he had received One hundred thouſand Crowns, of which he had given no account; he joyned himſelf with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de S. André,</hi> under pretence of preſerving the Religion of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors: But the truth is, it was only fear of being obliged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fund; and all that could be ſaid by his Son the Mareſchal <hi>Mortmorency</hi> (repuced the Wiſeſt Man in the Kingdom) was not of power to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him.</p>
               <p>This League, which the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes</hi> called <hi>The Triumvirate,</hi> being augmented by the acceſſion of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57675:65"/>King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that accompanied him as Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General of the Kingdom; the <hi>Hugonots</hi> forſook <hi>Paris,</hi> where the Catholicks were prevalent. The Proteſtants were no ſooner in the Field, and the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> at the head of them, but they began to make their Enemies tremble, as their Enemies had made them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Catholicks would not propoſe it to the King to return to <hi>Paris,</hi> becauſe the Prince of <hi>Condés</hi> party increaſing daily in their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, it was not impoſſible but they might ſeize upon the Kings perſon. To prevent the miſcheifs of ſuch an accident, the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the Conneſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repaired to <hi>Fountainbleau</hi> with all ſpeed, where they found the Queen heſitating and uncertain which party ſhe ſhould take; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, ſhe was weary of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> it is ſaid,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57675:65"/>that the Prince of <hi>Condés</hi> Religion appeared more commodious to her, then her own: The Hiſtory menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a Letter which the Queen-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writ to him ſome few days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which he ſent afterwards to all the Proteſtant Princes in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> to provoke their aſſiſtance; the words of it were theſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I Watch only for a favorable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to embrace your Party, and perhaps your Religion. Have you a care on your ſide, and act prudently, that after ſo great an advance, I may have no cauſe to deſist. On my part, I will omit nothing that may deliver me from the oppreſſion I am under; I know what meaſures I am to take to lull and infatuate the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> and when they believe me the best Friend they have in the World, I ſhall let them ſee, That in <hi>Italy</hi> there is no ſuch Vertue as Sincerity. Conſider the great confidence I repoſe in you, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57675:66"/>that I do intrust you with my Sons Interest, the Kingdoms, and my Own.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>It was a ſtrange ſurpriſe to the Queen-Mother, to find her ſelf preſſed by the Confederates, to bring the King back again to <hi>Paris.</hi> Before ſhe could put her ſelf under the protection of the Prince, ſhe expected till his Army ſhould be ſtrong enough to conſtrain the reſt of the Kingdom, to the expulſion of the <hi>Guiſes;</hi> and becauſe daily, Gentlemen were obſerved to repair to him, from all the Provinces in <hi>France,</hi> to tender him their ſervice, ſhe thought that time was not far off, and therefore expected it with the more patience.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations obliged her to temporiſe, and her deſign was as ſoon as the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and his Aſſociates were returned to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> to take a contrary Road, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57675:66"/>carry the King to <hi>Orleans;</hi> which was the place of the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dés</hi> Rendezvous, and the cheif re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable of his Party. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> having had long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of her cunning, told her, That the Perſon of the King was too dear to them to be truſted out of their ſight, in ſo tickliſh a conjuncture; and the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> (who was naturally frank) added, That for her ſelf ſhe might ſtay if ſhe pleaſed, but there was a neceſſity that the King muſt go along with them; and calling for his Coach, they carried him, with tears in his eyes, to <hi>Melun</hi> that night; the next day to the <hi>Bois de Vincennes,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Paris;</hi> where, under pretence of magnificence, they placed a ſtrong guard about him.</p>
               <p>The Prince was much troubled when he underſtood the King was in his Enemies hands, and thinking at firſt it had been a trick of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57675:67"/>Queens; he took all ways that he could invent to revenge himſelf of her. He publiſhed a <hi>Manifesto,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating, That the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> was entred into intelligence with the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> to keep their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign in durance; and to juſtifie what he ſaid, he inſerted the Queens Letter to him, and offered a ſight of the original to any Man that ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it. There was ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability in what he affirmed, That all who were impartial, and not of the <hi>Guiſes</hi> Party abſolutely, made no ſcruple to believe it. However, thoſe who were Neutral, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the one party, nor the other, got together in troops to demand the inlargement of their King; and their numbers increaſed ſo faſt, that they grew formidable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, inſomuch, that they were obliged to procure a Declaration from him (which they diſperſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Provinces of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom)
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57675:67"/>importing, That their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties were perfectly at liberty, and had choſen <hi>Paris</hi> as a place more proper for their ſafety; that to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jole the <hi>Hugonotes</hi> who had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to have ſeiſed upon the King, the Queen-Mother had thought it convenient to flatter them with fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous hopes, and to wheedle the cheif of their Party, with a Letter that had ſucceeded as ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
               <p>This Declaration was followed with an Arreſt of the Parliament, permitting any Man to murder the Proteſtants where-ever they met them, as perſons guilty of Treaſon both againſt God and their King. Nevertheleſs, no hoſtility having been committed either on one ſide, or the other, the Chancellor <hi>de l'Hoſpital</hi> (one of the wiſeſt men of his time) uſed all his intereſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate a ſtorm that had been gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and condenſing ſo long: But
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57675:68"/>his endeavors were ineffectual; the War brake out in ſo many places together, that nothing but a ſhower of Blood could extinguiſh it.</p>
               <p>Love, which commonly is not to be found, but amongſt ſports and recreations, had the courage to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all theſe dreadful preparations for a Civil War. The King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> having made a ſecond attempt upon the Vertue of the Mareſchals Lady, and with as little ſucceſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to looſe no more time about her, but to comfort himſelf againſt his repulſe there, by making his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to Madamoiſelle <hi>de Rouet,</hi> (a Maid of Honor to the Queen) and one that was not like to be ſo inexorable. On the other ſide, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>de Limevil</hi> her Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Maid of Honor to the Queen, as ſhe was, (whom the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> had formerly loved, and arrived at ſuch familiarity with her, as was for ſome time an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57675:68"/>to her) made it her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as much as poſſible, to convert his impatience to be fighting, into another paſſion, where ſhe found the combat was not altogether ſo unpleaſant. She knew his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and did not doubt, how va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant ſoever he was, but he was as ſenſible of Love, as of Honor. She writ to him, and deſired him to conſider, That he was making War againſt a perſon, for whom he had formerly had more kindneſs, for her Religion had placed her among his Enemies.</p>
               <p>This Letter not having the effect that ſhe expected, ſhe writ to him a ſecond, but to no more purpoſe then the firſt: At which ſhe was ſo highly offended, that for ſome time ſhe was mortally angry with her ſelf, that it was not in her power to hate him.</p>
               <p>The Queen (who during the War, had but an imperfect enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:57675:69"/>of her Regency, becauſe all things went thorow the hands of the Lieutenant General of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) underſtanding by Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de Rouet</hi> (to whom the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> had diſcovered it) that the Mareſchal <hi>de S. Andrés</hi> Lady had a great influence upon the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> ſhe ſent for her privately, and conjured her to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy her utmoſt authority, to make him conſent to the Peace; promiſing ſhe would never be unmindful of ſo great an obligation. Had Madam <hi>la Mareſchal</hi> durſt to have truſted her with her intrigues, ſhe would have done as the Queen had deſired. Her paſſion for the Prince increaſed every day; and though ſhe had Vertue enough to reſiſt, ſhe had not Vertue enough to triumph. She knew that to encourage his Troops, and animate them againſt all danger, he would be ſure to ſhow them an example, and expoſe himſelf firſt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:57675:69"/>where the danger was greateſt; and this thought gave her ſuch great and frequent anxieties, that under pretence of being ſolicitous for her Husband, ſhe conjured him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, as the Queen did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. In the mean time, the diſtance of the Prince was a torment to her; yet the reputation that ſhe had to be the perſon of the leaſt ſcandal in the whole Court, corrected her natural inclination: For the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of her Honor, ſhe renounced her affection, and would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired greater eſteem, had ſhe been always of that mind.</p>
               <p>The Queen diſguſted that Madam <hi>la Mareſchelle</hi> refuſed to write to the Prince; and being deſirous to know whether he had any kindneſs for her or not, reſolved to write to him her ſelf.</p>
               <p>After ſhe had diſplayed the beſt Arguments ſhe could think of, to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:57675:70"/>perſwade him to conſent to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, and repreſented to him, That the King (to whom ſhe had the honor to be Mother) the State, and her ſelf, ſhould be indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him for their repoſe; ſhe added, That thereby he would likewiſe do a ſingular favor to Madam <hi>le Mareſchalle,</hi> who would have writ to him her ſelf, if it might have been done with ſecurity: And to clear all doubts, that he might conceive in his mind, ſhe would bring her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Mont le Hery,</hi> if he thought good to meet at a day that ſhe would appoint (attended only with fifty men, and ſhe with the ſame number) to confer about ſome way of preventing a War, in which the happieſt ſucceſs that could be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, muſt needs be fatal to <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince thought no pleaſure equal to a ſight of his Miſtreſs, and therefore returned anſwer to the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:57675:70"/>Queen, by the ſame Meſſenger, That he would not fail to attend her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at the Rendezvous, where ever ſhe thought fit to command. The Admiral, who was by that time come to <hi>Orleans,</hi> was of another opinion: He underſtood the Queen ſo well, that all overtures from her were ſuſpected by him; but when Love ſpeaks, for the moſt part no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can be heard: So that it is no great wonder, if all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that the Admiral applied to the contrary, had no effect upon the Prince.</p>
               <p>The day the Queen had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed being arrived, the amorous Prince appeared in ſight of <hi>Mont le Hery,</hi> and the Admiral ſuſpecting ſome ſtratagem againſt his perſon, put himſelf into his equipage, and made one of the fifty; though he was not able to divert him from meeting, yet he perſwaded him from truſting himſelf in a Town that
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:57675:71"/>was inclined to the intereſt of the <hi>Guiſes;</hi> which reaſon was ſufficient to make him ſuſpicious. The Queen came thither the day before; before ſhe came out of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded two of her Maids to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves ſick, that ſhe might have a more plauſible pretence, to take along with her Madam la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle <hi>de S. André,</hi> and it ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſhe deſired: For the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal was ſo far from giving any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that he ſeemed to be much ſatisfied with the great honor the Queen conferred upon his Wife. The Prince having ſent a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the Queen to remonſtrate, that her forces were not equal where ſhe expected him, and to deſire he might attend her at a little Village betwixt <hi>Mont le Hery</hi> and <hi>Bretigny,</hi> where their Paroles could not on either ſide be ſo eaſily broken; the Queen departed immediately to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that place, accompanied with
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:57675:71"/>fifty Gentlemen, and the Chancellor <hi>de l'Hoſpitale</hi> who was in the ſame Coach with Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Prince, and the Admiral, perceived her Majeſty coming, they advanced to meet her; and when they were arrived at a competent diſtance to be ſeen, they alighted from their Horſe, and forgot nothing that was incumbent upon them, to the Mother of their King. Though Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe,</hi> and the Prince, were equally impatient of ſeeing one another, yet they ſpake not a word: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, where there is Love in the caſe, there are other ways of ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their minds; and it is no new thing, among them, to diſcourſe by the eye.</p>
               <p>The Queen had appointed the Chancellor her ſpokſman, and he made ſeveral Propoſals for Peace; but whether the Prince came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57675:72"/>only to ſee Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe,</hi> or that his mind being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupied, was not enough ſettled to come to a reſolution, in ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a matter, he did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with any thing that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. The Admiral, perſwaded that if Peace were concluded, he ſhould not be ſo conſiderable as the Prince; and beſides, having ſecret advice that they talked of cutting off his head, he made Propoſals al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his turn; but ſo unreaſonable, that they began to ſuſpect he had ſome intimation of their deſign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſon; and that if the Prince were of the ſame mind, it would be to no purpoſe to think of an accommodation: However the Queen would not deſiſt; and it may be ſaid to her praiſe (ſuppoſing always that ſhe meant as ſhe ſaid) that the offers which ſhe made were ſo reaſonable, that the Peace would have been infallibly concluded, had
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:57675:72"/>not the Admiral perverted the Prince by his ill Counſels.</p>
               <p>After two hours conference, they parted, and nothing concluded, the Prince and Madam <hi>la Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> who had not ſeen one another but in the preſence of the Queen, and were afraid on both ſides, leaſt their eyes ſhould have been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the explication of their minds, ſeparated with extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry regret.</p>
               <p>Both parties were now at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable diſtance, when the Queen unwilling to be any ways defective in ſo generous a point, ſent for the Prince to come back, and deſired Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> to alight out of the Coach, and privately to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure him from the intereſts of the Admiral. She obeyed her Majeſties commands, and the Prince ſeeing her make towards him, advanced to ſave her the pains, and quickly arrived at the place which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:57675:73"/>He caſt his eyes about, and ſeeing no body near enough to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what he ſaid, <hi>Ah Madam!</hi> cryed he, <hi>how cruel a thing is it to love! To ſee, and not to have the courage to ſpeak!</hi> Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> apprehending ſhe was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Queen, told him upon what account ſhe was commanded to meet him, and deſired to know what he intended to do. <hi>Let us leave, I beſeech you Madam,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>theſe affairs of State, and ſeeing our time of being together is ſo ſhort, be not ſo unkind as to deprive my love of any part of it: For in ſhort Madam</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my heart is too entirely yours to ſuffer you to be ignorant of its condition. I muſt confeſs I do but equivocate with the Queen, but I have too great honor for you to uſe any colluſion; and the peace which I refuſe, may aſſure you, that my coming hither was more to injoy the happineſs of your ſight, then to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:57675:73"/>entertain propoſitions of that nature. And what will be the effect of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview,</hi> replied the Lady, <hi>if we muſt immediately part, and perhaps never to ſee one another again? If the ſight of me was ſo dear to you, as you would have me believe, you would not leave me ſo eaſily, and the terms which are offered you, would ſeem reaſonable enough to prevail with you, to embrace an occaſion that might give you more frequent acceſs. Alaſs Madam!</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Prince, <hi>how unhappy ſhall I be to leave you, if your kindneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues. The hatred I retain for the</hi> Guiſes, <hi>is not proof againſt thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable ſentiments which you have been pleaſed to expreſs towards me: And although it will have great reflection upon my honor, to leave the inſolencies committed against me unrevenged, yet I ſhall wave them with delight, if the ſacrifice of my reſentments may, in any meaſure, convince you of the greatneſs of my paſſion. I require nothing of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:57675:74"/>your love,</hi> (replied the Lady ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fiercely) <hi>that may be a prejudice to your honor. If the esteem I have for you, be any ways conſiderable, it is to your own reputation alone, that you are indebted: And as great a Prince as you are, perhaps I ſhould not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily have granted it, had not you been a greater Man, and your merits been more venerable than your dignity. I cannot but tell you,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>it is a great trouble to me, that the Peace is not concluded; but it would be much more, ſhould any thing be patched up to your diminution: I ſhould be ſo far from interpreting the ſacrifice of your honor, to be an expreſſion of your love, that I ſhould underſtand it a weakneſs that would make me repent the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice of my choice; and if you will give me leave to advertiſe you with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, my heart, at preſent charmed with the greatneſs of your exploits, would eaſily diſabuſe it ſelf, if any thing ſhould eſcape wherewith you
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:57675:74"/>might be equitably reproached.</hi> The Prince overjoyed to hear what he did, replied with a tranſport, he could not conceal. <hi>How infinitely happy am I, Madam, to find ſo much generoſity in a perſon I ſhall adore as long as I live? How dear to me must my honor be, that is ſo much conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by your Ladiſhip; and if my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits were acceptable to you, before it was my deſign to pleaſe you, what ſhall I not do now to augment a reputation that renders me ſo much a debtor to your goodneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After which, he told her upon what grounds he refuſed the Peace, repreſenting to her, that the <hi>Guiſes</hi> were in poſſeſſion of a place that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to his birth; and he was in equity to diſpute it, though they had been advanced to it by their merit. <hi>As to Religion,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I do not intend that ſhall be any impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my fortune; nor have I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this (of which I make profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57675:75"/>now) becauſe it was the better, but in oppoſition to the Houſe of</hi> Lorrain, <hi>and that I might be their enemy: For let me but revenge my ſelf for the affronts which I have received from them, and it imports not of what Religion I am. What ſhall I ſay to the Queen?</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> in a manner that expreſſed the trouble ſhe conceived to leave him. <hi>She ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects your anſwer, and you know her impatience. In the name of that thing which is moſt dear to you in the whole World,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>do not haſten a ſeparation that will be ſo irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to me. The affairs which the Queen has committed to your conduct, are not of ſo little conſequence to be ſlubbered over in haſte, and perhaps I may never again have ſo happy an opportunity of ſeeing you. But Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe with great tenderneſs, <hi>if we ſhould be longer together, what ſhould we ſay? Ah Madam!</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>had I given as much love
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:57675:75"/>as I have received; what is it we ſhould not ſay?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farewel Sir,</hi> cried Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchelle</hi> (who perhaps began to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect her own continence) <hi>I am mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and it is enough to tell you, can hear you no farther. If you have any value for my eſteem, you know upon what terms it is to be obtained, and how you are to comport to deſerve it: But as dear as your honor is to you, I would not have you purchaſe it at too great a rate, nor be too prodigal of a life, for which perhaps I have a greater concern then you imagine. Once again adieu;</hi> and with thoſe words ſhe took her leave of the Prince, who conjured her to ſtay ſome few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments longer; but ſhe told him, That it was no argument of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to have ſo little care of her reputation; and his love being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with great reverence and reſpect, he ſuffered her to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and contented himſelf to wait
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:57675:76"/>upon her with his eyes till ſhe came to the Queens Coach; into which ſhe was no ſooner entred, but he faced about and returned to the Admiral.</p>
               <p>This Conference having no better ſucceſs, and the Forces on both ſides being near, acts of hoſtility were begun, and the King reduced to an unfortunate neceſſity of conquering his own Kingdom; <hi>Roüen</hi> having declared for the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> was the firſt Town that was beſieged. It en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſeveral aſſaults, with a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution that would have gained it much honor, had the cauſe been as good as their courage; but at laſt, the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> having in vain, endeavored to relieve it (the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de S. André</hi> having blocked up the Paſſes) it was taken by ſtorm, and the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> entred in triumph thorow the Breaches.</p>
               <p>This action was great, and made a great noiſe, but it was bought
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:57675:76"/>very dear: For the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> receiving a ſhot in his ſhoulder (which had not been dangerous, but for the too frequent viſits of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>du Ruet</hi>) it proved ſo ill, that putting himſelf upon the <hi>Seyne</hi> to go back to <hi>Paris</hi> by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a ſhivering took him by the way; and after that a cold ſweat, which obliged him to ſtay at <hi>Ande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis;</hi> where the ſame day he died as he lived, that is to ſay, in the ſame uncertainty as to his Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither true Proteſtant, nor good Papiſt.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> who had promiſed himſelf great honor from this expedition, and knew it to be the only way to ſtrike deep into the heart of Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André,</hi> was much dejected at the loſs of <hi>Roüen:</hi> However whileſt the Kings Army was imployed in <hi>Normandy,</hi> it came into his mind, to advance with his Army to the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:57675:77"/>very Walls of <hi>Paris,</hi> hoping that the ſuddenneſs of his approach, and the confuſion it muſt needs bring upon ſo large and populous a City, might make its conqueſt more eaſie; but his ſucceſs in that was no better, then in his relieving of <hi>Roüen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the miſcarriage of ſo great an enterpriſe, he thought it inglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to retire; and therefore choſe rather to advance againſt the Duke of. <hi>Guiſe</hi> (who was coming with his victorious Army from <hi>Roüen</hi>) and to engage him, if poſſible, to a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle that might revenge the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots,</hi> for the loſs which they had ſuſtained.</p>
               <p>The Admiral was of the ſame opinion, and they had doubtleſs defeated the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> had their conduct been as good as their courage: But their deſign being more talked of then was neceſſary, the Mareſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> came up with his Troops, and joyned with
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57675:77"/>the Royal Army, which had need enough of their Succors. The Prince was at the head of 12000 Men, and the number of the Catholicks was no leſs. They met near the Town of <hi>Dreux,</hi> and the two Armies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn up in Battalia, the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> charged with that vigor, that at firſt all the advantage was on their ſide. They made themſelves maſters of the beſt part of the Catholicks Cannon, and took the Conneſtable <hi>Montmerancy</hi> priſoner; but being allured by the ſplendor of the Train, and the hopes of Booty, they put themſelves out of order to plunder the Enemies Baggage; which the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (who was a great Officer) obſerving, he took the opportunity, charged again, and improved the advantage of their confuſion ſo well, that he turned the ſcales, and forced the <hi>Hugonots</hi> out of the Field. The Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> in the greateſt heat
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:57675:78"/>of this charge, advancing in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> found himſelf in the midſt of a Party of Catholicks, who demanded his Sword; but inſtead of giving them an anſwer, he made uſe of it to make his paſſage; but finding it to no purpoſe, he delivered it to <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> the Conneſtables ſecond Son, and yeilded himſelf his priſoner: Whileſt the Catholicks were in this manner engaged with the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> a Body of the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Horſe having made a charge upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal <hi>de S. André</hi> (who was too hotly in purſuit of the victory) they put him to the ſame diſtreſs, took him priſoner, and were carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him off to accompany the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtable: But a <hi>Pariſian</hi> called <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziers,</hi> who had been formerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged by him, took that oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to revenge himſelf, and ſhot him dead upon the place.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:57675:78"/>
               <p>The Admiral, with the relicks of his <hi>Hugonot</hi> Troops, recovered <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans</hi> with all ſpeed, apprehending, that if he were charged again, he ſhould be forced to quit the Conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> was preſented by <hi>Danville</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who treated him with a reſpect, accompanied with many marks of eſteem, which were return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo much generoſity by the Prince, that it was an aſtoniſhment to them both to conſider, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great deference and civility they expreſſed one to the other, that yet they ſhould be ſo unhappy as to be Enemies.</p>
               <p>Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dré,</hi> whoſe vertue had hitherto been unſhakable, was much troubled for the death of her Husband: But the news of the death of <hi>Eleonora,</hi> Wife to the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> arriving preſently after, gave her no ſmall relaxation. She had received a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:57675:79"/>from the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> dated after the Battle of <hi>Dreux,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her againſt the loſs of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; and ſhe to requite it, had condoled with him with the ſame ceremony upon the loſs of his Wife: But the deſign was only to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe one another, that thoſe impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being removed, they were now at liberty, and needed not any longer reſtraint. In the mean time, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (who had gained great reputation by the greatneſs of this exploit) was unwilling to give the <hi>Hugonots</hi> breath) the moſt of whoſe great Officers being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, he concluded the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity too favorable to be ſlipped; and <hi>Orleans</hi> being the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Town of their party, he thought by forcing of that, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to a neceſſity of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what terms and impoſitions he pleaſed to exact.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="151-196" type="pages">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:57675:79"/>
               <p>He began that ſiege the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> and in ſpight of the extreamity of the ſeaſon, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Garriſon, poſſeſſed himſelf of all the Suburbs with the loſs only of eight or nine men; but riding out one evening to meet his Lady, who was at that time coming to the Leagure; the infamous <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trot</hi> having watched him three or four days before, ſhot him treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with a Piſtol, of which he died ſix days after, to the infinite regret of all that knew him, and particularly of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> who (though his Enemy) could not forbear giving teſtimony of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at his firſt notice of the news. All the Catholick Hiſtorians, and even thoſe whoſe Religion he would have deſtroyed, have thought it an honor to do Juſtice to his memory; and though they were not of the ſame ſentiments in point of Religion, yet in this they agreed,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:57675:80"/>That he had all the neceſſary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of a Gentleman, without any of the vices, either of a Prince or a Courtier.</p>
               <p>Leaſt he might leave a ſtain upon his memory, he imployed almoſt the laſt moments of his life, in clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf of the maſſacre at <hi>Vaſſi;</hi> calling God to witneſs, That it was innocently, and without deſign, if he was the occaſion of the War. He adviſed the Queen-Mother to take the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> near to the Perſon of the King, his quality making it injuſt to keep him at a diſtance; and this he propoſed as the only way to accommodate all quarrels, and reſtore peace to the Nation.</p>
               <p>The Queen, who judged of other people by her ſelf, and looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of a dying man to be ſincere, made uſe of the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> Counſels, ſuppoſing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſuddenly to give an account
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57675:80"/>of them to God, he had delivered himſelf freely without artifice or cunning. She proſecuted the Peace, and whileſt ſhe was before <hi>Orleans,</hi> cauſed the two priſoners, the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and the Conneſtable to be brought under good Guards, to a place called <hi>l'Iſle aux Baeufs.</hi> The Prince, who by the death of his Lady was become Maſter of himſelf, and knew that Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> was at as much liberty by the death of her Husband, was impatient to ſee her, and deſired Peace with all the eagerneſs of the World: But the fortune of his Arms having been unkind ſince he ſaw her laſt; and knowing that ſhe was ſenſible ſo much of nothing, as of honor and renown, he would willingly order it ſo, as the Treaty of Peace ſhould revenge the injuries of the War, and had rather remain a priſoner eternally, then ſign any thing that Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> ſhould not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:57675:81"/>After ſeveral meetings, in which both Parties had propoſed, and conteſted their ſeveral intereſts, a Model was drawn up, of which the Prince deſired a Copy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending he would ſend it to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, who at that time was about <hi>Havre de Grace,</hi> in order to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a ſum of Money out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> wherewith Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſupplied the <hi>Hugonots</hi> privately: But he ſent his Copy ſecretly to the Mareſchal <hi>de S. Andrés</hi> Widow, with a compliment (the higheſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable) That the Peace or the War, depended upon her direction; and which ſhe in her great wiſdom would vouchaſe to appoint, that he would ſtand to, and nothing elſe. This tranſcendent expreſſion of love (which left her arbitrix of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs or unhappineſs of the whole Kingdom) made great impreſſion upon her heart: She was more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amored with that, then ſhe had
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:57675:81"/>been ever before: And if ſhe had had no love for him, ſhe could, not in honor but make him ſome ſuitable return. She did ſo, and the Letter which ſhe ſent, was doubtleſs as he would have deſired; for within eight days after, the Peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
               <p>This great work having in a ſhort time ſtifled all Diviſions, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Animoſities in all parts of the Kingdom; the Queen had thoughts not to return ſo ſodainly to <hi>Paris,</hi> but to carry the King tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſome of his Provinces, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with his Subjects, and that he might gain upon their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The Conneſtable and the Chancellor <hi>de l'Hoſpital</hi> attended them, but the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> had other avocations. It was but a days journey betwixt <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> and in a days time he might be gone; yet it was a long time to his impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:57675:82"/>
               <p>It was about midnight before he could get to <hi>Paris,</hi> but no hour is unſeaſonable for love: The Prince being of that opinion, alighted where his love had conducted him; and Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with the news that he was come in, and deſired permiſſion to ſee her, was ſo much diſcompoſed, that it brought a colour into her face, that added new luſtre to her beauty. After they had ſaluted, and great compliments paſſed on both ſides, the Prince perceiving they were alone, and that in civility the Ladies attendants were retired out of the Room. <hi>I must have much love Madam</hi> (ſaid the Prince to her) <hi>or great confidence in your goodneſs, to appear in your preſence, having ſo ill obſerved your preſcription. Honor was the only way, by which you directed me to your heart, which I have been ſo far from acquiring ſince our unhappy ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that I have done nothing but
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:57675:82"/>contributed to the glory of the Enemy, and that in ſo high a degree, as to make him maſter of my Liberty, to which condition, no body had any title to reduce me, but your ſelf. Your Fame Sir,</hi> replied the Lady, <hi>has prevented you, and gives us an account of your carriage without any diſadvantage to your honor. It was not in flying from your Enemy, that you was ſurrounded and taken; and when I recommended to you the care of your reputation, it was not with deſign to object to you the malice of your fortune.</hi> The Prince underſtood by the obligingneſs of her anſwer, that the diſgrace which he had received at the Battle of <hi>Dreux,</hi> had not alienated the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> and that was enough for one viſit. Being late in the night, and having found her undreſſed, he thought it but civil to take his leave, which he did, and departed ſooner then he could have wiſhed, and perhaps
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:57675:83"/>ſooner then Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> her ſelf deſired. The next morning he was to wait upon her again. He himſelf was in mourning, and found her in the ſame dreſs, wherewith both parties were well pleaſed. For for one time when that habit is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually ſorrowful, there are a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred when people are joyful to wear it. The Prince had children by his Wife, but Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> had none by her Husband, who had left her a conſiderable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, of which ſhe was not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to any body. The year (during which, they were obliged to ſome kind of <hi>decorum</hi>) being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly expired, Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe,</hi> not having had power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear loving the Prince, when her vertue and fidelity to her Husband impugned it, loved him now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, where ſhe might do it without crime; and he took too
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:57675:83"/>much pleaſure in the owning it, to deſire it ſhould be a ſecret.</p>
               <p>A certain Gentleman of <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> called <hi>Montſequiou</hi> (whoſe greateſt qualification was to be a Captain in the Duke of <hi>Anjous</hi> Guards) with a confidence natural to his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; caſt his eyes upon Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> and believed, that having the favor of his Maſter, he was in a condition high enough to pretend to the Widow of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was a Man of wit, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf admiſſion, he obtained to be ſent to the ſaid Lady with a compliment from the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> upon the death of her Husband. Having diſcharged himſelf well of this Embaſſie, and poſſeſſed her, that he was a perſon of ſome parts, he made her ſeveral viſits afterwards upon his own account; and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored to inſinuate into her affection by his reſpects, of which, the <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigns</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:57675:84"/>are no niggards, eſpecially when it conduces to their deſigns.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> being one of the moſt conſiderable matches in the Kingdom, <hi>Monteſequiou</hi> was fearful leaſt ſome body ſhould get before him, and therefore took his firſt opportunity to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; at which Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> was much ſurpriſed, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him with ſcorn, ſhe told him, That did ſhe not believe ſhe ſhould diſparage her ſelf by publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his confidence, ſhe would have made him preſently to have repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; and then turning away, ſhe forbad him her preſence for ever.</p>
               <p>This Gallant, whoſe quality was not great enough to permit him to revenge himſelf publickly, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the cunning of inferior ſpirits, and did what he could to deprave and blacken the reputation of the Lady.</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:57675:84"/>
               <p>The kindneſs which ſhe had for the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and he for her, was the diſcourſe of the whole Court, and it was given on the Ladies ſide, that hers was moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; and that which made it the more credible, was a preſent that ſhe had made him, great enough indeed to cauſe it to be preſumed, that it was the recompence of ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſervice. After the Dukes of <hi>Anjou</hi> and <hi>Alencon,</hi> the Kings Brothers, there was no body but the young Prince of <hi>Bearn</hi> (who was ſince <hi>Henry le Grand</hi>) nearer the Crown then the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and yet this latter (though a Prince of the Blood) was but narrow in his fortune, and could not make any expence proportionable to his quality.</p>
               <p>The Mareſchals Widow could not ſuffer ſo little a defect, in ſo conſiderable a Man; ſhe took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in correcting the injuſtice of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:57675:85"/>Fortune; and <hi>Valery</hi> being one of the beſt of her Mannors, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured him to accept it, and gave it in ſo good earneſt, that the Princes Heirs enjoy it at this day. To gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie her kindneſs, (and perhaps to oblige her to ſomething elſe, which I will not mention in this place, and which malicious people ſay ſhe never refuſed him) the Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her Marriage, and had married her immediately, had he believed the Peace firm enough, to have lived quietly with her. In the mean time people talked diverſly of this Act of Bounty in the Widow: For one perſon that commended it, there were ten who reproached it; and there hapned at the ſame time to be a Poet who exerciſed his vein upon it, and made two Couplets to the the tune of a Courant that was then in mighty requeſt.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:57675:85"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
                  <body>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When the mutinous Stars, call him forth to the Wars,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Succeſs the Prince always purſues.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And Love in that caſe, thinks it fit to embrace</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ſame ſide that Vict'ry does chuſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To this fortunate Prince (fear'd and lov'd ever ſince)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His dear an Eſtate did Demiſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Without telling its name, you may gueſs at what game</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Twas his Highneſs got ſuch a Prize.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe Verſes made more noiſe then they were worth: <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> was one of the firſt that had got them; and to revenge himſelf of his Miſtreſs, he gave Copies of them to any body that asked them: And when at laſt they were ſuſpected to be his, he denied them in ſuch a manner as perſwaded people it was true, though indeed he was none
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:57675:86"/>of the Author. There being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Song, but what either was, or was thought to the Princes advantage. It was not long before it was ſung to him; but he who ſung it, was not ſo wiſe as he might have been. The Prince deſired the Copy, and asked him if he knew the Author; he told him it was <hi>Monteſquious</hi> hand, and that he had made them himſelf.</p>
               <p>At his departure from thence, going directly to Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challes</hi> Lodgings, he found her in a greater rage then ever he had ſeen her, and it was not long before he underſtood the occaſion. One of her intimate friends had brought her a Copy of the ſame Verſes, which ſhe had heard ſung alſo, and inquiring of the Author, it was ſaid to be <hi>Montſequiou.</hi> Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle</hi> had no mind to acquaint the Prince with the affront ſhe had already received, becauſe ſhe would
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:57675:86"/>not trouble him with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he had ſo inconſiderable a Rival: But inraged as ſhe was, ſhe could keep no meaſures, but uſed all means poſſible to revenge her ſelf of his inſolence. The Verſes which had been given to the Prince, and thoſe which were brought to Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> were written both in a hand, which confirmed the ſuſpition that <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> made them. This incenſed the Prince ſo highly againſt him, that as <hi>Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiou</hi> was one night returning alone from the <hi>Louvre,</hi> he met with thoſe who gave him an hundred good blows with a Weapon, not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo honorable as a Sword; and leaſt he ſhould be ignorant from whence that beating came, they told him it was a preſent from the Prince of <hi>Condé.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This aſſault made a greater noiſe then the Verſes: The Queen, who loved the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:57675:87"/>took it very ill that the Prince ſhould treat one of his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers at that rate: But there was too much inequality betwixt them, for the Prince to make any excuſe; and beſides, ſince the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> misfortune, there was ſcarce a Gentleman in <hi>France,</hi> but would have ſided with a Prince of the Blood.</p>
               <p>Things were in this poſture when the Admiral (who was not at all pleaſed with the Princes paſſion for Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André</hi>) propoſed a match to him with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>de Orleans,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Longuevilles</hi> Siſter, who was young, and handſome, and a better fortune then the other. Some are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and have not ſpared to report it, that the Prince had obtained of Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle,</hi> that which ſhould never be granted to any Man, whom a Woman deſires to make her Husband: For this is a
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:57675:87"/>certain property of love, to deſire without end, and when nothing is left to irritate that deſire, love ceaſes, and takes no pleaſure in any thing it receives. However though the Princes heat began to ſlacken every day, yet he was ſo far ſenſible of the favors which he had enjoyed from the Lady Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André,</hi> that he rejected the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals propoſition at firſt, as knowing how inſufferable it would be to the perſon in the whole World, to whom he had the greateſt obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Yet his deſign was to leave her by degrees, and to reſtore her Mannor of <hi>Valery</hi> that ſhe had given him ſo generouſly; that he might diſcontinue inſenſibly, he forbore his viſits at firſt for two days, then four, and next a whole week. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> thinking every hour loſt that was not ſpent in his company, complained of him ſo tenderly, and reproached his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:57675:88"/>in ſo gentle and innocent terms, that privately the Prince could not but accuſe his own obduracy, in not anſwering ſo incomparable a kindneſs.</p>
               <p>One day as ſhe deſired him to make no more Proteſtations, but perform his promiſe; he gave ſuch poor and trifling Reaſons to excuſe it, that after ſhe had uſed the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of her power to conceal her ſorrow, and was ſcarce able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her tears which were ready to break forth before his face, ſhe could not but tell him. <hi>Then Sir, I ſee your love is at an end. Conſider better of your ſelf Madam,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>and do not ſo much injustice to your own Excellency, to believe one can be ſo eaſily delivered from your Bonds: Were not my love for you ſo great as you deſerve, the bounty that you have expreſſed towards me, would eternally preſent it ſelf to my memory, and my heart is too well placed to be
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:57675:88"/>guilty of ingratitude. Ah Sir!</hi> ſaid Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle, it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments that I ask of you, it is love: If I have done any thing for you that deſerves to be remembred, that was my deſign; and if you do not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it, I have done nothing that I intended to have done.</hi> The Prince (who hated ingratitude, and yet found himſelf too much diſpoſed that way) made uſe of all his wit to diſpel that fear which Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> had entertained; but his heart had not the leaſt ſhare in what ever he ſaid. As ſome people love to ſee every thing in the beſt place, and let no opportunity eſcape, wherein they may flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo ſhe believed whatever he would have her, and even repented that ſhe had ſo injuſtly ſuſpected him. Thus they parted, ſhe more then ever in love with the Prince, and he diſtracted with the remorſe that thoſe perſons feel, who though
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:57675:89"/>indued with a great deal of vertue, are yet at the point of falling into a crime. He ſuffered almoſt a moneth to paſs, and never made her a viſit, becauſe he could not get from her without trouble; yet he writ to her every morning, and made the faireſt excuſes he could contrive to render his abſence ſupportable. At laſt having pumped himſelf dry, and no reaſons left to make his apology, the truth could be no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed.</p>
               <p>One night as Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> was alone in her Cloſſet, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over all the Letters that ever ſhe had received from him, and (where ſhe found them kind) watering them with her tears; word was brought, that there was a Gentleman without, who deſired to ſpeak with her from the Prince. He was brought in, and having preſented her with a Packet, ſhe opened it haſtily, and found it in theſe terms.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:57675:89"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>IT is too much to abuſe your credulity, Madam, and multiply my own crimes together. I cannot longer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear acquainting you, that I betray you; and that inſtead of favors and kindneſs, you ought to oppreſs me with diſdain. Would to Heavens you had hated me ſix moneths ago! I ſhould, at least, have had ſome pretence for my ingratitude; and if I had ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Reaſon, I might poſſibly have ſeparated without remorſe; but fix my thoughts upon what object I can, I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee nothing but obloquy. My memory is full of your goodneſs, mine eyes of your beauty, my heart is convinced of your love, and yet I write to you now the last time, and am constrained, by the malevolence of my destiny, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the honor of ſeeing you any more. I know you are ſo kind as to love me, and that I do wound you in your moſt tender and most ſenſible part; but it ought ſomething to ſupport
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:57675:90"/>you, that I do it with leſs prejudice to you, then to my ſelf, ſeeing I lament what I looſe, and you looſe nothing that you have reaſon to lament. In fine, Madam, being guilty against my will, I do not deſire you ſhould have occaſion to hate me for detaining a thing that I must confeſs I hold of your love. I restore therefore your <hi>Valery</hi> which I cannot keep but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly; and as for my life, which I ow to your goodneſs, I ſhall ſpend it ſo miſerably, and it will last but ſo little a while, that you will not have long to upbraid my perfidiouſneſs. Farewel Madam, I will not tell you with what ſorrow that word came from me; you will be able to judge of that by the grief that will follow, and I ſhall let you ſee, that it is more torture to me to commit a crime, then to puniſh it.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>In what condition was the poor Lady upon the reading of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; her heart was great, and ſhe
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:57675:90"/>thought complaints too mean to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporate her ſorrows that way. <hi>Here, Sir, carry back this Paper which came in the Letter that your Master troubled himſelf to ſend me</hi> (ſaid ſhe to the Gentleman who brought it) <hi>and tell him from me, that he does not restore all that he had from me, and I cannot abſolve him for ſo little.</hi> The Gentleman made ſome difficulty to receive it, but ſhe gave him ſuch Reaſons, that at laſt he could not handſomely refuſe. It was the Grant which Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> had given to the Prince of <hi>Valery,</hi> which he thought diſhonorable to retain having quitted the Lady. But though it was a preſent worthy of him, when he accepted it; yet ſhe thought it beneath her to take it again upon thoſe terms; nor could ſhe prevail with her ſelf, to reſume that from an ingrateful perſon, which ſhe believed ſhe had given to the moſt faithful of his Sex.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:57675:91"/>
               <p>When ſhe found ſhe was alone, and under no neceſſity of conſtraint, ſhe gave her ſelf up wholly to grief, which her love and indignation fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented continually.</p>
               <p>It is certain the Prince was all this while in as great an agony as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>la Mareſchalle.</hi> The moneth that he had ſuffered to paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing her, had been imployed in negotiating his marriage with the Duke of <hi>Longuevilles</hi> Siſter; and leaſt Madam <hi>dé S. André</hi> ſhould give any impediment to it, with the promiſe that had been made her by the Prince; the Admiral had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it ſo cunningly, that though it was a marriage of great importance, it was to be conſummated that very night, without being known to above five or ſix who were to be preſent.</p>
               <p>This muſt be ſaid in favor of the Prince, and all people muſt agree to it, that he had many conflicts and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:57675:91"/>combats within himſelf, before he could conſent to that infidelity. The kindneſs which Madam <hi>la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle</hi> had ſhown him, before he had given her any occaſion: The tenderneſs wherewith afterwards ſhe had given him ſuch tokens of her affection. The deſperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to which he foreſaw ſhe muſt, of neceſſity, be reduced: In ſhort, whatever came into his thoughts, when he remembred her, cauſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and compunction in his heart, and the nearer the time approached in which he was to give himſelf to another, the more his ſorrows in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. But the Admiral who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> himſelf, and could not endure ſhe ſhould be beloved by any body elſe, ſtirred not from the Prince till the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was conſummate; the influence that he had upon him, being too ſtrong for all the Princes reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:57675:92"/>
               <p>This Wedding that was kept ſo ſecret (leaſt his promiſe to Madam <hi>la Mareſchelle</hi> might have diſturbed it) ceaſed to be a ſecret, when there was nothing to fear, and the next day the new Princeſs of <hi>Condé</hi> went in that quality to pay her firſt homage to the Queen.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>la Mareſchelle</hi> was in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> at the ſame time; and knowing nothing as yet of what had paſſed the night before, ſhe looked upon her only as Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>d'Orleans,</hi> not imagining why the Page that carried up her Train, ſhould be in the Princes Livery; but ſhe enjoyed this ignorance not long; for in a ſhort time, they told her what ſhe was not willing to have known.</p>
               <p>She went immediately from the <hi>Louvre,</hi> being unable to endure ſo ungrateful an object. As ſhe was going away, ſhe met <hi>Monteſquiou,</hi> and, in ſpight of her malice to him,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:57675:92"/>conjured him to follow her. She was no ſooner in her Chamber, but he was called up, and carried into her Cloſet, where being not to be heard by any body but himſelf, <hi>Do you love me ſtill</hi> Monteſquiou? ſaid ſhe to him. <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> ſurpriſed at the demand, but more at the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of delivering it, imagined the cauſe, and gueſſed it muſt be rather anger, then love that made her ſo kind. However not loving with the <hi>punctilio</hi> of a Gentleman, and it being indifferent to him upon what Motives ſhe married him, ſo it was but his fortune to carry her, he told her, <hi>That he loved her, without intermiſſion, from the very first time he had ſeen her; and though he was ſo unhappy as to lie under her diſdain, yet it was ſtill his reſolution, and he would love her whileſt he lived. Theſe are but words,</hi> replied Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle, I have been too lately, and too unworthily betrayed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:57675:93"/>ſuch weak testimonies again. If you love me, you muſt ſhow it by more effectual evidence; and let me tell you the evidence I require of you, is not to be performed by a perſon of mean or indifferent courage? Conſult your love before you give me an anſwer, and ſee if it be capable of doing a piece of ſervice for me, that ſhall be worthy of being recompenced with my ſelf. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it Madam,</hi> replied <hi>Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiou, and you ſhall ſee how far my paſſion will carry me. The reward that you are pleaſed to propoſe, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to encourage me against the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est difficulties; and to have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of your Ladiſhip, is an honor, for which no enterpriſe is too great. You ſpeak as if you would do as you ſay,</hi> replied Madam <hi>de S. André, and in that confidence I ſhall tell you the means by which you may merit the recompence that I deſign for you. I loved the Prince of</hi> Condé; <hi>you know it well enough, and the outrage that
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:57675:93"/>he cauſed to be committed upon you (which it is now high time to revenge) made all the World believe he had as much affection for me. I know it is ungrateful to you, to be remembered of this point, but I do it on purpoſe to awaken your reſentment: It is no matter to which of us the vengeance belongs, ſo you take from him that life which he had long ſince reſigned, had I been ſo wiſe as to have left him to his deſtiny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſider what it is you propoſe Madam,</hi> replied <hi>Monteſquiou, and when your firſt tranſports are paſſed, will you not repent of your commands? Do you think me ſo fickle,</hi> replied Madam <hi>de S. André, and that my heart is ſo poor to forgive the injuries that are done me? If I repent of any thing, it will be, that I concerned my ſelf for a perfidious perſon, unworthy of my care and ſolicitude; that I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed all my pains to an ungrateful man, who remembers ſo ill thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:57675:94"/>which he never deſerved; and in ſhort, That I have pulled upon my ſelf by the force of my generoſity, the affront of which I complain to you, and you refuſe to revenge. This,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>is all I have to repent of; but do not think that I will ever do it, of a thing ſo juſt, as what I now purſue: The prize that goes along with it, ought to have made you undertake it without farther expostulation; but ſince you heſitate, I may perhaps have leſs trouble to perſwade another, then to work upon you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is enough Madam,</hi> replied <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſquiou, I am reſolved and ready for what ever you command. I feared leaſt your affection to the Prince, had been ſtill ſo great as to have prompted you to be the first that ſhould exclaim against me, when the buſineſs was done; but I am ſatisfied now, that your deſire is too fervent, not to hear of it with pleaſure; and ſeeing it is me you have choſen for this great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:57675:94"/>I ſhall take my meaſures ſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and purſue them with ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſhall not bring you under the leaſt ſuſpition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ask no other ſecurity of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>then your own word. I have too much honor for you to inſiſt upon a Note under your hand, in ſo tickliſh an affair; beſides though there is nothing ſo dear to me in the World, as the price you have been pleaſed to ſet upon my ſervice; yet I ſhould think I rendered my ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of it, if I ſhould ſtand to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it with ſo immodest a precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This unhappy converſation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ſome time, and ended at laſt in a promiſe that <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> reiterated again and again, not to let many days paſs before he brought her the news of the death of the Prince of <hi>Condé.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had ſhe known what the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> ſuffered for her, whileſt
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:57675:95"/>ſhe was conſpiring againſt his life, it is moſt certain ſhe would never have been carried to ſo violent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. He loved her as well as ever, and his kindneſs to his Wife was cold and indifferent; at firſt it was no little trouble to the new Princeſs, but ſhe accuſtomed her ſelf to it by degrees, and finding that ſhe was not ſole Miſtreſs of his heart, we are aſſured, by very cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible <hi>Memoires,</hi> ſhe made him as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Maſter of hers. But which way ſoever it was, the Prince made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral vain efforts to diſintangle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle;</hi> but the impoſſibility of injoying her now, made her appear the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable, and never was his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo ſtrong to marry her, as now he had another Wife.</p>
               <p>Her viſits to the Court were not ſo frequent as before, leaſt ſhe ſhould meet the Prince, or the new Princeſs whom ſhe hated as much:
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:57675:95"/>But having ſome occaſions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe could not diſpence, he met her two or three times, and made it his buſineſs to accoſt her; but her care to avoid him, was as great, and ſucceeded much better. However that was not ſufficient to diſcourage him; he was many times to wait upon her at her Lodgings, but ſhe was never at home for him; and her orders were ſo exactly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that as ſoon as any of his Liveries appeared, the Gates were ſhut up, and no more opened that day.</p>
               <p>It troubled him exceedingly to find ſo much unkindneſs, yet he could not be ſo partial, but to know he deſerved it. At laſt preſſed by the violence of his paſſion, he could ſubſiſt no longer without ſeeing her. To live in her diſpleaſure, was a very great torment; and how great ſoever his offence was, it was leſs then his remorſe.</p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:57675:96"/>
               <p>One Morning when the Porter was more remiſs then he ſhould have been, he conveyed himſelf in at the Gate, and ran directly to the Chamber where he uſed formerly to ſee her, ſuppoſing he ſhould eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſurpriſed her; but by ill fortune for him, ſhe had changed her appartment ſince he ſaw her laſt, and having timely notice that the Prince was to viſit her, ſhe retired into her Cloſſet, and ſhut the door to her, reſolving he ſhould break it open rather, then ſhe would ſee him.</p>
               <p>This ſeverity did not make him forget the reſpect which accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his paſſion: He conjured her on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to let him have the honor to ſee her; and to oblige her thereunto, he ſaid ſo many kind things, that ſignified ſo much the ſincerity of his ſorrow, as would infallibly have prevailed, had ſhe been capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of forgiving him. But let him
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:57675:96"/>ſay what he could, he was married to another, and the very thought of that put her into a fury that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her deaf to all his ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He was a compleat hour beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging moſt earneſtly, that ſhe would but grant him the honor to ſee her, though for as ſmall a time as ſhe pleaſed; but being after all his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity unable to obtain any anſwer, but a few angry words which he received with the greateſt ſubmiſſion, he retired rather then be troubleſome any longer; and within a few days removed to <hi>Noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> in <hi>Bourgogne</hi> (which was a Houſe belonging to his new Lady) to ſee if abſence, that is one of the uſual remedies of love, could cure him of that wherewith he was ſo cruelly tormented.</p>
               <p>He had not been there long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two Soldiers were apprehended, meaſuring the Wall of the Caſtle, which they deſigned to have ſcaled.
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:57675:97"/>They were brought in and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and finding themſelves in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be very ill treated, unleſs they diſcovered the truth, they confeſſed they had done it by order from the Queen, and the Cardinal of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who had reſolved to ſurpriſe and exterminate all the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots;</hi> and that they might do it with more eaſe, it was concluded to begin with the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> as their head. It is moſt certain, this was reſolved in Council, and the Admiral who was at <hi>Taulay,</hi> with <hi>Dandelot</hi> his Brother (to whom that Houſe belonged) had already ſome inkling of it. The Prince not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far from them, diſpatched a Courrier immediately, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them much in what they were but jealous of before, becauſe they had had it from a perſon of but ordinary quality. Had they not inſtantly united and retired out of that Province, they had been cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:57675:97"/>by a party of Horſe, which came into <hi>Bourgogne</hi> on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but when the ſaid party found they were gone with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of an hundred and fifty Horſe, they purſued them as far as the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Loire,</hi> where they had paſſed at a Ford not far from <hi>Sancere.</hi> Scarce was the Prince clear of the River, and firm on the other ſide, before the Kings Troops appeared, and might eaſily have got over at the ſame Ford. But Evening com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, the Officers thought it more convenient to defer it till the next Morning, and in the Night the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſwelled ſo violently, that it was not fordable any where; which putting a ſtop to the purſuit of the Catholicks, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> looked upon their preſervation as a miracle. The Prince, the Admiral, and <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delot,</hi> being ſo ſtrangely delivered, retreated to <hi>Rochel,</hi> where in a few days time they had a general Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:57675:98"/>of all their own Troops, and Four thouſand Men brought to them by the Queen of <hi>Navarre.</hi> The Kings Army commanded by the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> remained in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne; and <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied his Maſter, left not <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> without renewing to Madam la Mareſchalle <hi>de S. André,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which he had made to ſacrifice the life of the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> to her reſentment; but his flowneſs had made her often repent, that ſhe had committed the care of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge to a Man of ſo little reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>She attended with great impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to hear the news of what he had done, when one Afternoon, as ſhe returned from ſome viſits, which ſhe had been making abroad, her Porter delivered her a Letter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to her, and brought by one of the ordinary Meſſengers of the Poſt-Office. The character of the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:57675:98"/>ſuperſcription, and the Seal being unknown to her, ſhe opened it, and was exceedingly ſurpriſed to find it came from the Prince of <hi>Condé:</hi> Her firſt thoughts were to tear it without reading, but her curioſity to know what he could expect after ſo great infidelity, overpowred her indignation, and prevailed with her to read it: But all the choller wherewith ſhe had fortified her ſelf (leaſt by ſeeing it, ſhe ſhould be any ways melted) could not defend her againſt the love that he expreſſed in it. The poor Prince, who to ſpeak proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rather endured, then took com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his life (ſo unhappy he thought himſelf to have contracted the hatred of his Miſtreſs) had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to her (as his laſt remedy) from <hi>Rochel,</hi> to endeavor, if poſſible, to mollifie her: And if he could not ſucceed, his reſolution was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate himſelf into ſo many deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:57675:99"/>actions, as would in proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility afford him ſome perſon that might revenge his infidelity.</p>
               <p>This Letter was writ ſo much like a Gentleman; his excuſes ſo cordial, his contrition ſo likely, and ſomething elſe there was ſo paſſionate and moving, that alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they coſt Madam <hi>la Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challe</hi> no few tears before ſhe could read them thorow: Inſtead of that fury which had poſſeſſed her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the fear leaſt <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> ſhould be too faithful in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of her commands, was the thing which wholly took up her thoughts: She writ to him with all ſpeed, and deſired him to ſuſpend the execution of his promiſe till farther order.</p>
               <p>He received the Letter, and found by the alteration of her ſtile, that the deteſtation which Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> had had for the Prince, began to abate, and that
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:57675:99"/>if ever they came together, their love would certainly revive.</p>
               <p>To make her believe her Letter never came to his hands, he would give her no anſwer, but accuſed his own lazineſs for not having kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Prince ſooner.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> (who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps gueſſed what was the deſign of his ſilence) writ again to <hi>Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiou,</hi> and forbad him in expreſs terms to execute a command that ſhe had laid upon him in her rage, but diſapproved ſince ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the uſe of her Reaſon. This Letter exaſperated <hi>Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiou</hi> ſo highly, that what ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to prevent the deſtruction of the Prince, haſtned it; and made her Agent the more vigorous in its execution.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, finding <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> would return her no anſwer, but ſtill continued his ſilence, ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched a Meſſenger to him on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:57675:100"/>with a third Letter, which ſhe charged him to deliver into his own hand, to take from him all poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of excuſe.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the two Armies approached and came within ſight of one another, where they lay for a fortnight together skirmiſhing, and in defiance. The Kings Army was more numerous by one third, but the Princes Army conſiſted of better and more reſolute men; and therefore they promiſed themſelves the victory, if they could bring the Enemy to a Field Battle.</p>
               <p>The Prince, who knew nothing of what paſſed in the mind of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de S. André,</hi> and was weary of his life, becauſe he thought it was become indifferent to her, adviſed by all means to preſs the Enemy to a Battle, which the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> being young, and of leſs experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, declined. However after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral charges and pickeerings, which
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:57675:100"/>did but tire and harraſs their Troops, an opportunity was offered, and they muſt of neceſſity come to a general engagement.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hugonots</hi> were quartered at large along the River <hi>de Charente,</hi> and had poſſeſſion of the Bridges at <hi>Jarnac</hi> and <hi>Chaſteau-Neuf,</hi> which was a great diſadvantage to the Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Armand de Gontaud-Biron</hi> who commanded under the Duke of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou,</hi> undertook to beat them from their Poſts, but not being able to carry <hi>Jarnac</hi> by ſurpriſe, he turned toward <hi>Chasteau-Neuf,</hi> which the <hi>Hugonots</hi> deſerted after they had broken down the Bridge; but that was repaired again ſo ſuddenly by the care of Monſieur <hi>Biron,</hi> that the Kings Army was paſſed over be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Hugonots</hi> perceived it.</p>
               <p>The Princes Army being divided and diſperſed in ſeveral places, the Admiral ſent Orders to the Foot to
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:57675:101"/>draw off towards <hi>Baſſac,</hi> whileſt the Cavalry got together from their fartheſt Quarters: But Monſieur <hi>Biron</hi> took advantage of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and diſturbed their Retreat ſo vigorouſly, that they had much to do to defend themſelves. The Admiral was making head againſt <hi>Biron,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in favoring the Retreat of his Troops, when the Admiral ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him word to advance, and that there was need of his preſence; he came in upon a gallop to his releif, and fought with ſuch reſolution, that in ſpight of the inequality of his Forces, he diſingaged the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, and drew upon himſelf the whole fury of the Catholicks. At length (not able to bear up againſt ſo great a number of his Enemies, and (to increaſe his misfortunes) his Horſe being wounded, and falling down under him at the ſame time) he preſented his Gantlet to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:57675:101"/>called <hi>Argence,</hi> who received him with all the reſpect that was due to his quality.</p>
               <p>The report of his being taken, was carried immediately to the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and the unlucky <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> being by, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Prince's Leg was broke with the kick of a Horſe, and that in that condition, it was not poſſible for him to defend himſelf; he clapped Spurs to his Horſe, and gallopping up to him, found him ſitting under a Buſh, in which poſture, pulling out one of his Piſtols, he ſhot him into the head, and killed him. This is mentioned by our Hiſtorians, as one of the moſt infamous Actions that was ever committed.</p>
               <p>The Prince died without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one word; and although the Meſſenger which was ſent from Madam <hi>la Mareſchalle</hi> made all poſſible ſpeed, yet the buſineſs
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:57675:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>was done before her Letter arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>The firſt news of that diſaſter put her into an abſolute diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but having recollected her ſelf, by degrees ſhe fell into a ſettled and deliberate melancholly that laſted as long as ſhe lived; and when, at his return, <hi>Monteſquiou</hi> came to demand his recompence, ſhe looked upon him as the greateſt Monſter that Nature had ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hugonots</hi> having loſt ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a Cheif, made but little progreſs in their affairs afterward. <hi>Dandelot</hi> died a while after, ſome ſay of the grief, he had conceived, for the death of the Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> and others ſay, he died of a Peſtilential Feaver. The Admiral lived till the maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> day, of which, he being the principal cauſe, was made the principal victime.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57675:102"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
